<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Munster and Abingdon, or, The open rebellion there [brace] and [brace] unhappy tumult here (bred in the same wombe) that from Sleidans Comm. L. 10. [brace] [brace] this from eye and eare witnesses : with marginal notes of Mvncer and Mahomet, faithfully communicated to English readers, in a booke and postscript, for a seasonable caution to the British nation and a serious check to rash and giddy spirits / by W.H.</title>
            <author>Hughes, William, fl. 1665-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39005</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18206026</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 18206026</idno>
            <idno type="VID">107072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1125:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Munster and Abingdon, or, The open rebellion there [brace] and [brace] unhappy tumult here (bred in the same wombe) that from Sleidans Comm. L. 10. [brace] [brace] this from eye and eare witnesses : with marginal notes of Mvncer and Mahomet, faithfully communicated to English readers, in a booke and postscript, for a seasonable caution to the British nation and a serious check to rash and giddy spirits / by W.H.</title>
                  <author>Hughes, William, fl. 1665-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 110 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hall ... for Robert Blagrave,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Hughes by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>John, --  of Leiden, ca. 1510-1536.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Germany --  Münster.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Abingdon Or the</hi> Open Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
<hi>there,</hi> and Unhappy Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult <hi>here. (Bred in the ſame
wombe)</hi> THAT From <hi>Sleidans</hi> Comm. L. 10. THIS From eye and eare
witneſſes. With Marginall Notes of <hi>MVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CER</hi> and <hi>MAHOMET.</hi>
Faithfully communicated to Engliſh Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in a <hi>Booke</hi> and
<hi>Poſtſcript,</hi> For <hi>A ſeaſonable Caution to the Britiſh
Nation.</hi> And <hi>A ſerious check to raſh and Giddy ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>W. H.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Tim. 3, 1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>In the laſt daies perillous times ſhall come; for men ſhall
be lovers of their owne ſelves—deſpiſers of thoſe that are good,
Traytors, heady, high minded &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 24.24.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets
—inſomuch that (if it were poſſible) they ſhall deceive the very
Elect.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mark. 13.37.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>What I ſay to you I ſay to all, WATCH.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD.</hi> Printed by HENRY HALL Printer to the
Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, for ROBERT BLAGRAVE. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107072:2"/>
            <head>The Books Requeſt.</head>
            <p>Heare me, <hi>but</hi> out, <hi>My Judge,</hi> before Thou
ſentence paſs; I'le ask no more.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:107072:2"/>
            <head>The Tranſlators Preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Serious Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Husbandman</hi> was not more diligent to ſow his
<hi>corne,</hi> than the<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.25.</note>
               <hi>Enemy</hi> was to ſcatter <hi>tares</hi> among it. The Event doth prove
this was no leſſe <hi>propheticall</hi> than <hi>Hiſtoricall.</hi> Where
ever was a <hi>Chriſtian Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> ſet on foot, but a
<hi>Deviliſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> dog'd it at the very heeles? Let a <hi>Church
for Chriſt</hi> be ſetting up, 'tis hard but <hi>Sathans Chappell</hi>
mates it. To <hi>ſpie abroad</hi> for obſervations of this kind is to
overlooke the <hi>beame at home.</hi> Aske but the ſeven yeares paſt with
us, and you ſhall quickly find, <hi>this land</hi> hath not injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its
<hi>Sabbath</hi> from this ſort of <hi>Sowers</hi> yet. Not, but that we
ſee, <pb facs="tcp:107072:3"/>and thankfully acknowledge a hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full harveſt of better
fruits. But when the <hi>Laborers</hi> are ſo few alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that a deſigne
ſhould drive ſo <hi>Jehu-like</hi> to keepe off <hi>others,</hi> yea turne
off <hi>theſe,</hi> (though ſuch as Chriſt hath ſet on worke, and
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered in it to the bringing in of <hi>all,</hi> or <hi>moſt</hi> that
are not yet abroad) to <hi>turne off theſe,</hi> I ſay, ſure this makes
plaine to halfe an eye <hi>there, is no freind at worke.</hi> Yet do not we
<hi>ſee</hi> thoſe ſpirits, wide as <hi>Dover</hi> and
<hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle</hi> from one <hi>another,</hi> and <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> too
oft, meete here? And to cry downe the <hi>publique Miniſtry,</hi> as eager as
they to cry up <hi>(b) Diana?</hi> A plot,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi>
19.28.</note> whether leſſe <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or <hi>Humane,</hi> I
cannot tell. Let me ſay nothing, the thing it ſelfe will ſpeake, that
ſince their time, who were immediately called from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the
<hi>Godly-learned Miniſters</hi> were the men that planted, water'd, yea and
ſoyld <hi>with their very blood</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:107072:3"/>the Church of Chriſt in
every age. Were they not <hi>thoſe</hi> that, under God, did firſt deliver
<hi>our ſoules</hi> from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian bondage at the utmoſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of
<hi>their owne bodies?</hi> Witneſſe <hi>Luther, Zuinglius, Caluin:
Latimer, Ridly, Hooper, Bradford,</hi> and that cloud of others ſtaked at the
fire in England. Who elſe have beene the <hi>ſpirituall Fathers</hi> to the
thouſands of faithfull holy ſoules (now gone to heaven) for the hundred
yeares laſt paſt, with us and other places: yea, and begat to grace and
knowledge thoſe (therewith endued) whoſe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence now againſt them
labours to make requitall with worſer than <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiering</hi> for their
ſervice? Which were it once effected, and no publique Miniſtry longer left
among us, into what a <hi>dolefull, heatheniſh, helliſh, plight,</hi>
thoſe many hundred pariſhes (too ignorant and prophane already) in theſe
Nations would be quickly caſt? ſpecially ſince we ſee the Devill 
<pb facs="tcp:107072:4"/>and his drudges are not idle, <hi>Reader,</hi> let thy ſad
thoughts reſolve thee. O diſmall day when Judgment ſends a famine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11</note> not of bread but of the word of
God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nu.</hi> 21.5.</note> upon a Land that fell to
loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it! We know, <hi>with God all things are poſsible,</hi> but know
not, why to looke for miracles, and leave off ſuch a courſe himſelfe
<hi>appoynted,</hi> and from heaven ſo long and often hath <hi>approved.</hi>
And then for inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, what is more barbarous than that ſo many hundred
families of Godly Miniſters, to whom we are ſo nearely related <hi>as
men,</hi> in a manner of the ſame fleſh and blood with our ſelves; and to
whom we owe ſo much <hi>as Chriſtians,</hi> ſhould, <hi>for no other
fault but their well deſerving at our hands,</hi> be turned out of their
propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and ſent a begging, againſt all <hi>right</hi> and
<hi>reaſon,</hi> as we ſpeake, all <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Conſcience?</hi>
Bleſſed be God, our former Governours have waſhed their hands of any
ſuch like <pb facs="tcp:107072:4"/>buſineſſe, and we nothing doubt but that ſuch
ſpeciall grace is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with thoſe now preſent at the <hi>Helme</hi>
that they will continue to abhor it. And we truſt, through mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,
notwithſtanding all the <hi>catching</hi> at the <hi>ſtirrup</hi> by ſome
furious ſpirits, they never ſhall be able to <hi>diſmount</hi> the
<hi>Riders</hi> to get themſelves into the <hi>ſaddle.</hi> Let what there
will be <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt</hi> tis ſadly feared (if not plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt)
ſuch a buſineſſe lyeth at the <hi>bottome.</hi> Should which time come,
what <hi>fence</hi> another mans propriety can get when the Miniſters ſhall
lie <hi>common</hi> you'le quickly <hi>ſee unto your Coſts.</hi> Meane
while, for a Comment on the whole, <hi>Reader,</hi> Ibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech the read &amp;
well conſider the enſuing ſtory: where thou ſhalt Find <hi>a pretended
zeale for ſetting up Chriſts Kingdome on the earth made uſher</hi> (oh
moſt dreadfully!) <hi>to the verydregs of villanies ſpit from
Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth of which ſaid <hi>ſtory</hi> on <pb facs="tcp:107072:5"/>underſtanding and indifferent perſon will ever call to queſtion.
But yet becauſe <hi>abſurdities</hi> are ſo much <hi>in faſhion,</hi>
let me intreat the ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſon (for ſuch there are too many) to
conſider what beames of evidence he ſhuts his eyes againſt: How likely is
it we ſhould be abuſed in a buſineſſe—</p>
            <p>Firſt, So <hi>publique:</hi> not done in a Corner,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>This Story</hi> 1. <hi>Publique.</hi>
               </note> but the
principall City of Weſtphalia, Munſter. 2. So ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Councils ſitting in
the Empire about it. 3. An Army of many thouſands rayſed for it. 4. And a
ſiege almoſt a yeare and halfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the City, ere it could be taken:
<hi>with yet much more like that.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. <hi>La'e Anno.</hi> 1517
<hi>Ann.</hi> 1536</note> and ſo <hi>late:</hi> After <hi>Luther</hi> had
began the Reformation ſome nine-teene yeares, and now juſt ſixſcore
ſince thoſe ſtirs were ended.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Neare.</hi>
               </note> ſo
<hi>neare us:</hi> not in Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, <pb facs="tcp:107072:5"/>China or the Indies (though
thence we have intelligence that goes for currant) but in Germany, and that
part thereof that borders on the Low Countries: <hi>almoſt at home.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">4. <hi>And having multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of
Authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tique Authours.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>that hath ſo many credible Authors.
Luther, Melanct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hon, Bullinger, Menius,</hi> and <hi>Rhegius,</hi> with
ſcores of others, <hi>were it worth the while,</hi> that might be named. And
now theſe, 1. ſo far from Papiſts, as firſt reſtorers of the
Goſpell. 2. Men of eminent piety. 3. That lived in the ſame Country. 4. At
the ſame time, ſpectators, in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, of the whole buſineſſe from
firſt to laſt. And for this Author M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Sleidan;</hi> He was a
Proteſtant, one fearing God, and then living there, and of great eſteeme
and credit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all profeſſors of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and deſervedly
famous for his writings to paſt, and preſent, and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ages: and
which is of ſpeciall <pb facs="tcp:107072:6"/>notice, one <hi>that tooke not any thing
upon</hi> meere hereſay, <hi>but all ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his</hi> owne knowledge,
<hi>or out of</hi> publique Records.</p>
            <p>He that will not yet believe it, doubts happily of our bloody
<hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an daies,</hi> the <hi>eightie eight Invaſion,</hi> the <hi>powder
Plot,</hi> the <hi>fight at Edg-Hill.</hi> It may be whether <hi>the woman,
that bred, and brought him forth, be his owne mother.</hi> And ſo is worthy
not of <hi>words</hi> but <hi>ſtripes</hi> for gaining his aſſent.</p>
            <p>Touching the Tranſlation, onely thus much. It was ſo much my
<hi>care,</hi> (ſome happily will call it <hi>ſuperſtition</hi>) to tread
exactly in the <hi>Authors ſteps</hi> (ſaving the diviſions into
chapters, and contents thereon) that I would not <hi>ſtep aſide</hi> to
take up any the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties of our <hi>Engliſh ſpeech</hi> that lay on
either hand as we paſſed along. But this too, as the reſt, is humbly
caſt at ingenuous Criticks feet.</p>
            <p>If any ſay; Sure thoſe with us <pb facs="tcp:107072:6"/>againſt
<hi>Infant Baptiſme</hi> are not of kin unto the <hi>Germanes</hi> mentioned
in this ſtory.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, That it is no doubt with me, but that many Godly,
precious ſoules are found amongſt them, whoſe <hi>hearts would
riſe</hi> at the very hearing of <hi>this helliſh tragedy:</hi> whoſe
ſoules eſtabliſhment in the grace of God we pray for, and whoſe
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian fellowſhip we gladly ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, and mourne to ſee the
<hi>folly</hi> that keeps them at <hi>ſuch a diſtance.</hi> Yet truly, in
this houre of temptation, <hi>many, many ſeeming ſtars have fallen from
heaven:</hi> and this <hi>our age</hi> hath ſpoken more, <hi>to carnall
reaſon</hi> for Saints finall Apoſtacy, than all <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minian
arguments.</hi> Yea, to ſpeake our hearts, whoſo ſhall pleaſe but
heedfully to feele the pulſe, and mark the face of many <hi>leaders now
adayes among them,</hi> I feare wil be too apt to ſay I find <hi>ſome John
a-Leidens Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</hi> For my part I will leave it <pb facs="tcp:107072:7"/>to the
Readers judgment, whether <hi>that Spirit</hi> that biddes ſo faire as both
at once to pull downe the <hi>publique Miniſtry</hi> and roote up the
<hi>ſettled Magiſtracy</hi> looke not ſo <hi>like him</hi> as if it were
his <hi>owne begotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a truth of Gods owne teaching,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> that <hi>the heart is deceitfull above
all things, and deſperately wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who can know it?</hi> And we our
ſelves by ſad experience have often learn't it, that many have thought it
utterly impoſſible for them, ever to <hi>incline</hi> unto ſuch wretched
cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as afterwards they have beene <hi>mad in.</hi> When the Prophet
told <hi>Hazael</hi> what miſchiefe he ſhould ſometimes do in
<hi>Iſrael.</hi> Is thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant a dog, quoth he, to do this? But the event
made it truer than he was aware of,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.13.
<hi>with</hi> 10.32, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 13.324, 22.</note> 
               <hi>whilſt be wanted
power to effect it.</hi> And truly <hi>Reader,</hi> here with us they are but
<hi>young daies</hi> yet: all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though, alas! every moment thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, <hi>but too
faſt,</hi> towards a diſmall <hi>noone.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:107072:7"/>
            <p>To conclude: this uſe, at leaſt, this ſtory ſerves us to:
that trembling to behold Gods righteous judgments againſt abuſed
kindneſſe, where ever we find this ſpirit working in another (thoug with
the ſmootheſt face) we ſtop it what we may: and for our ſelves to
<hi>watch and pray leſt we fall into temptation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head> 
            <pb facs="tcp:107072:8"/> 
            <pb facs="tcp:107072:8"/> The Hiſtory of <hi>John a-Leyden,</hi>
The Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt King in Munſter.</head>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. I.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The Introduction. Of <hi>T. Munſter.</hi> And Anabaptiſts in
generall.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee are coming now to the ſeige of <hi>Munſter,</hi> the
principall City of <hi>Weſtphalia:</hi> ſave that ſomething muſt be
fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fetched, even from the firſt beginning of thoſe ſtirrs till
their <hi>Authors</hi> puniſhment upon the taking of the City. Of
<hi>Thomas</hi> 
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:107072:9"/>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">The ſtory is
briefely thus: Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer having leſt the Preaching of the Goſpell, fell to
new Doctrine; inveighs not only againſt the Pope, but Luther alſo: At
firſt he taught againſt Prophaneſſe, would have the body Curbd with
faſting, and meane attire; was for a grave ſet face litle talke private
meditation &amp;c. Then we muſt aske of God a ſigne that he did love us,
and chide him too, if he gave us none: That God revealed his will in dreames;
that revelations with the Scripture muſt be our Rule, withall community of
goods did beſt become us; and all to be of equall ranke. At laſt, ungodly
Magiſtrates muſt be downe; in order whereto he gets <hi>8000</hi> men
toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and exherts them to fightagainſt their princes, by this time with
an Army neere them, tells them they knew t'was not his fancy, but Gods Comm and
that ſet them on this worke, And helpe from heaven ſhould make them
Conquerors: As for their Bullets he would receive them all in his owne Coate:
And Loe, ſaith he, what a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God we have! Behold the taken of his
everlaſting favours Lift up your eyes and ſee the Raine-bow in the Heavens,
which ſince we have its picture in our Colours, Showeth plainely God will be
with us in the Battell to our enemies Raine. At the encounter <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi>
Party is quick'y routed <hi>5000</hi> ſlaine in the field, <hi>300</hi> more
in a Towne they ran too: Muncer was hid in a houſe by the Gate: Thither comes
in a noble mans ſervant, to ſee the houſe: gets up the ſtaires, finds
one in bed, askes whether he be one of the Rebels. Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer ſaith, no: But
that he had beene ſick a great while of a feaver. The Servant Spyes apurſe
Catch'd it with hope to have a Prize, Opening he findeth letters unto
<hi>Muncer</hi> from the Earle of Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild to for beare Rebellion: Then askes
him whither they were ſent to him or not: on his denyall, the ſervant
threatneth to diſpatch him: he prayes him to hold; and confeſſeth he is
<hi>Muncer:</hi> Then on the Rack crying out for paine they bid him now
remember how many ſilly ſoules his Villany had deſtroyed to day. He with
a mighty Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſayes, Themſelves deſired it: Yet at the Point of
death he publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſed his fault. But for Example ſake his head
cut off was faſtened to a ſpeare and Placed in the miale of the Camp. This
was in Germany the yeare <hi>1525.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Muncer's</hi> his
ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion amongſt the Rable, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:107072:9"/>his doctrine and his end,
our fift booke made report. By him was hatched that brood of men who for their
Practiſe and opinion are called <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> of whom alſo
ſomething hath beene ſaid allready. 
<q>For they for bid Baptizing litle ones, are rebaptized
themſelves, affirming, All men elſe ſhould do the ſame, and cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
Null the former Bapiſtme. They pretend unto an outward dreſſe of
Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Teach Chriſtians ſhould not goe to Law, beare Civill
office, make oath, maintaine propriety, but leave all things Common.</q> They
began with Theſe; then, matters farre more beynous, as I ſhall ſhew anon.
And whereas <hi>Germany</hi> was farre and neere infeſted with them. Yet,
<hi>Luthers</hi> and moſt other learned mens oppoſitions to them, with the
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates narrower eye upon them tooke ſo, that they could hardly
<hi>Sowder into a Conſiderable Number.</hi> At laſt they fixed in the
aforeſaid City ſtrongly fortified.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:107072:10"/>
            <head>CAP. II. </head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>B. Rotman</hi> firſt brings the Goſpell to Munſter. The
Popiſh Clergy oppoſe. But in vaine. And are ſilenced.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>It fell out thus: hard by this Munſter is St Maurice Church; There
did one <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard Rotman</hi> in the yeare of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 1532, with
great Concourſe of the Citizens, preach the Goſpell, and when they had
ſome thoughts of getting him into the City, the <hi>Popiſh Prieſts,</hi>
to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it, give him a pretty ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes to exerciſe himſelfe
ſome other where. He takes his leave, and having veiw'd ſome Places where
he might im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove his parts, a few moneths after comes back againe. They, angry
at his returne, would faine have put him off from Preaching: But all in Vaine,
the People being taken with him. Soone after he is entertained in the City by
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Cheifeſt Citizens, and when the Church was ſhut againſt
him, they make a Pulpit for him in the Porch with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:107072:10"/>
            <p>But the number of the Citizens and his hearers encreaſing dayly.
They require the Preiſts to ſet open the Church, or they would breake it
up.</p>
            <p>In the Nicke of this, He, by Advice of <hi>thoſe the People
choſe theretoo,</hi> diſpatcheth letters into <hi>Haſſia,</hi> that was
neere them of the Lantgraves Juriſdiction, to deſire that ſome learned
Godly men might bee ſent unto him, there to ſow the Goſpell with him. Two
hereupon are ſent from <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgh.</hi> Upon their comming ſix of them
get together and conſult of the quickeſt courſe to ſet the Popiſh
Clergy packing, that the Goſpell might ſucceed the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The beſt
expedient found hereto was this; They draw up the Popiſh Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and digeſt
them into ſome thirty heads: Thoſe they deliver to the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Or Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell that Ruled the City.</note> Senate with this
reſolution, That if they 
<q>did not <hi>Prove</hi> by the <hi>word of God</hi> All thoſe
waged war therewith, they would ſubmit to any puniſhment.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ſenate Calls the Preiſts into the Court, and propoſe the
Errours whereof we ſpake. And becauſe they ever bare in hand their doctrine
to be pure, and groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on the word of God, which the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers now deny,
and offer to make good <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107072:11"/>upon their lives, 
<q>They aske them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would confute by Scriptures, what
ſhould be objected?</q> They, thus demanded, and perceiving that the Senate
was in very earneſt in the buſineſſe, make a ſhort Anſwer, 
<q>That they had juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to defend their cauſe withall, but
whereas hitherto they did pretend their way was right and good, twas from
opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and their Ignorance.</q> The Senate then, ſince they convicted of
their errors and falſe doctrine, could ſay nothing for themſelves, but
confeſſe their naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, command them henceforth not to medleany
more with taching, but give way in all the Churches to theſe new Teachers
that had unmasked their knavery. On this (the People too concurring with the
Senate) the Churches were Aſſigned to them reſpectively where to
teach.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:107072:11"/>
            <head>CAP. III.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The Biſhop inſtigated by the ſilenced Pricſts blocks up
the City, this party is ſurpriſed by the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens. Indentures of Peace are
mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally Signed.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THat Buſineſſe bred ill bloud among the Preiſts, them
eſpecially of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thredrall Church, for the moſt part all of Noble
Bloud. They, none other ſhift being left, depart in rage, applying to the
Biſhop of that City. Whereupon Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell had, it was reſolved to block up
all the waies, that no proviſion might come to the City. <hi>A</hi> little
after, the waies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all and every where beſet, the Biſhop with thoſe
of whom I ſpake, to promote their worke the better, comes unto
<hi>Tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get,</hi> a little Towne ſome one mile diſtant from the City.
Thence letters are diſpatched unto the Senate to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. 
<q>That they forbeare their Courſe, reſtore their former State,
or to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <pb n="8" facs="tcp:107072:12"/>as Enemies.</q> The Biſhop was Earle
<hi>Francis Waldec,</hi> next before him had beene <hi>Frederick,</hi> owne
Brother to the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Colen.</hi> But He, whether
becauſe he had not well his health there, or that he ſmelt out ſomething,
not long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of his owne accord had left the Place, and to live private,
returned him home into his Countrey. They of Munſter well pauſing on the
buſineſſe, deteine the Meſſenger, and the night before Chriſts
birthday about 900 Sallying forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked for take both the little Towne and
(making good the Gates that none might ſcape) All that were in it. The
Biſhop as fell out, was gone the day before. The priſoners were forthwith
brought into the City. Amongſt them were the eminenteſt of the Clergy, and
ſome alſo of the Nobility; The Senate askes them, what their pleaſure is,
&amp; if they meane to ſtop the Preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. They freely
Anlwer, Their endeavors ſhould not be wanting to promote that doctrine.
Hereon they ſtrike the bargain. A Copy whereof the Senate ſent the
Lant-grave, with all beſeeching for the Goſpels ſake and publike good to
have his helping hand. He ſendeth ſome of his <pb n="9" facs="tcp:107072:12"/>owne to
them: by whoſe Mediation t'was concluded, 
<q>that their hearts agreed, and diſtaſt removed, both ſides
ſhould cheriſh peace: The Goſpell to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in ſix Churches, all
ſuperſtitious and ungodly worſhip turn'd packing:</q> in the Cathedrall
Church, no alteration to be made, nor the City reckon that in any caſe
belonging unto them. This forme of their agreement was ſigned by the
<hi>Lantgrave,</hi> the Biſhop and his Party, the Nobility and all the
people, <hi>Feb.</hi> 14. the yeare of our redemption 1533.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Leiden arriveth. Starteth Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Rotman oppoſeth
publiquely. A diſputation is entred. Rotman revolts. And the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts
are baniſhed.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THings thus appeaſed, there came to Munſter a certaine
Holland<note n="(a)" place="margin">That is a mender of old Clothes.</note>
Botch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, one <hi>John a-Leiden</hi> an eager Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt. He at the firſt
inſinuating into a <pb n="10" facs="tcp:107072:13"/>familiar diſcourſe with them;
would uſe to aske the Preachers of the Goſpell whither they thought, that
Infants duly might be baptized, They ſaying, yea, He that was warped quite
Crooked on the other ſide, begins to laugh &amp; ſcorne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at. Which
taken notice of <hi>Bernard Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> (of whom before) exhorts the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
in his Sermon to pray that ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine 
<q>might be preſerved with them, and kept incorrupt from fanatique
Perſons, the Anabaptiſts eſpecially, who at this time did Creepe
amongſt them, and get in peoples company, whoſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhould it
prevaile woe, would it be, not only to the ſtate of Common-wealth but alſo
of Religion.</q> Juſt then, almoſt, comes thither <hi>Herman Strapeda,</hi>
who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made <hi>Rotmans</hi> Colleague, publikely Inveighs againſt
Poedobaptiſme. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter was one <hi>Henry Rolls,</hi> whom they of
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht</hi> (before this time a little) had pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for
Anabaptiſme. This fellow was indeed another ſtep to this new kind of
doctrine. And now the Buſineſſe was of ſuch a Pitch, that moſt of all
the talke about the City was of Anabaptiſts; Though things were yet but
cloſely Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed. For none could be admitted but <pb n="11" facs="tcp:107072:13"/>who were
of their Sect. And then the Authors did not openly profeſſe theſe things,
nor teach them, but by night; and when others were aſleepe then only were
their holy exerciſes. But the buſineſſe coming out, when very many of
the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens were enrag'd at it, crying out, 
<q>T'was baſe, an upſtart Tenet ſhould be ſcattered privily
and by night,</q> The Senate ordered, That the Authors ſhould be gone the
City. But they going forth return'd another way, Vapouring, That they had
Command from God to ſtay, and There, in earneſt to goe through with their
buſineſſe. This was a Trouble to the Senate and ſomewhat did amaze
them, and therefore to prevent diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and farther danger the Preachers
both of the Goſpell, and of Anabaptiſme are commanded their appearance at
the Court, and ſome learned men together with them. Then <hi>Rotman,</hi>
which he had conceal'd till now, ſhewes himſelfe; and condemneth
Paedobaptiſme as a wicked and accurſed thing. But <hi>Herman Buſch</hi>
eſpecially did ſo make good the other ſide before the Senate, That they
were by Publike Order Commanded forthwith <pb n="12" facs="tcp:107072:14"/>to depart the
City. Yet when they Pleaded that they could not ſafely paſſe the
Biſhops Countrey, The Senate both procured them publike faith, and alſo
gave proviſion for their Journey. But they who long before, reſolved not to
ſtirre a foot, ſtep privily aſide into their owne Aſſociates, and lie
cloſe a while.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The Lantgrave ſendeth Preachers. A freſh debate appointed.
And the termes rejected by the Anabaptiſts.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>MEane time the Senate, e're they might againe appeare above board,
ſhut all the Churches up, ſave onely one. For it was feared, leaſt the
Anabaptiſts, whoſe number dayly did encreaſe, ſhould with their
ſpeakers Tumble out the Preachers of the Goſpell from the Church. Then, in
the moneth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember the <hi>Lantgrave</hi> at entreaty of the Senate,
ſent them two Teachers, <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique Fabrice,</hi> and <hi>John
Melſinger:</hi> And this, perceiving the diſturbance, ſtartled 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107072:14"/>alſo at the danger, goes home againe. The other
vigorouſly admoniſhed the Citizens to keepe a jealous eye upon the
Anabaptiſts Doctrine. After which rate he held untill the Anabaptiſts
getting uppermoſt turned the others out of Towne, as you ſhall here anon,
And that nothing might be wanting, he drawes up a forme of doctrine &amp;
Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the Content both of the Senate and the People. Then,
with the Senates leave, <hi>Peter Wirtem</hi> begins to Teach againe. But a few
Sermons hardly over, by <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Inſtigation, the Anabaptiſts
caſt him out. Who now growing feircer challenge <hi>Fabrice</hi> and others
to a diſputation. The Senate likeing it, it was thought meete to have the
buſineſſe managed from holy Scriptures and other writings ſuting with
them: ſome honeſt learned men, as mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, to be joyned; who upon due
Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of the opinions and Arguments of either ſide, ſhould determine;
what they determined, to be ratifyed: So as at laſt, diſſentions laid
aſide, peace might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to the Church. But as for thoſe Tearms,
<hi>Rotman</hi> and his fellowes would none of them. When therefore they
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed Publique Teſt, they began to fall <pb n="14" facs="tcp:107072:15"/>into a
Generall contempt. To waſh off which ſtaine they find another more
com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Courſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Popular Tumults, And open Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection by Anabaptiſts. A
skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh and agreement.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ONe of them, like a man inſpired, runs through the City and cryes
out, <hi>Repent and be baptized or elſe the wrath of God will overwhelme
you.</hi> Here firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the vulgar Tumults. And all that were baptized
againe cryed out as he, and in his Poſture. Many enſnared by their owne
ſimplicity (men otherwiſe Honeſt) for that they feared the wrath of God,
whereof theſe made ſuch noyſe, come in unto them, and others too, to
ſave their ſtakes. For the truth is, the Anabaptiſts dealing courſly
with their Adverſaries did fairly turne them out of all. This was about
Decembers end. And now againe theſe peepe out of their holes, of whom I
ſpake before. Who with an outcry hurrying to the market place together, 
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107072:15"/>
               <hi>command all not bapts'zd to be put to death as Pagans
and ungodly wretches.</hi> Then ſeiz'd they on the Magazine and Hall, laying
violent hands on many. The others to defend themſelves and theirs, make good
another Certaine Place with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the City, by nature fortifyed, ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
very many of theirs. This skirmiſh againſt the Anabaptiſts that kept the
Hall and fenced it round held, till on giving Mutuall Hoſtages, They came to
Termes, where by it was provided, That every man ſhould keepe his owne
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion goe home and live at peace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Anabaptiſts ſend to confederates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. The City fills with
them. Poedobaptiſts maſtered. Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts rule. And fire the ſuburbs.
Baniſh diſſenters. And ſeize their eſtates.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>ROtman</hi> the while; and <hi>Bernard Cnip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perdoling</hi> the
very fore-man of that Gangue) although they gave their good <pb n="16" facs="tcp:107072:16"/>word unto this agreement, yet by their ſecret letters to the
Neighbour Townes encouraged all them of their ſtamp, <hi>That bidding adeiu
to whatſoever they had, they ſhould Poſt-haſt be with them there; looke
what they left behind they ſhould enjoy with Tenfold Intereſt.</hi> Such
ample and magnificent promiſes ſet on their way to <hi>Munſter</hi> both
men and women in the greateſt Number, with certaine expectation of enjoying
greater matters; The poorer ſort eſpecially that had not to live at home.
The Townes-men, cheifly thoſe of faire Eſtates, perceiving how the City
fild with ſtrangers, with as much Covenience as they Could, withdrew
themſelves, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving behind, the Anabaptiſts and the multitude. This was
about Shrove, Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in the moneth of February, 1534. When the other Party
had beene weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thus, The Anabaptiſts forme a new Senate, of their owne
Creatures all; and Create <hi>(a)</hi> Conſuls alſo,<note place="margin">Like
our Mayors; but they were too.</note> Cnipperdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for one. Within few dayes
they ſet upon <hi>St</hi> Maurice Church in the ſuburbs and fire both it
and all the building neare it. Then rob they all the Chnrches and tare downe
the inſide of the Cheifeſt. <pb n="17" facs="tcp:107072:16"/>By and by they run on
heapes through all the ſtreets, and firſt they cry, <hi>Repent,</hi> but
quickly after, <hi>depart from hence imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ye wicked ones, except you
meane to lay your lives at ſtake.</hi> Withall they are ſtrait in Armes
together, and whoſoever were not of their ſect, without more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe, they
thruſt them out of towne without reſpect to either ſex or Age. So as
indeed ſome women great with Child miſcarried in this tumultuous and
precipitant baniſhment. Immediatly they ſeize on their Eſtates they had
turned out. And notwithſtanding this befell the day before the Biſhop did
beſeige the City, yet of the multitude that were faine to leave it, ſome
falling into the Biſhops hands, were reckoned enemies: others in danger of
their lives, and among the reſt, two Preachers of the Goſpell. He of whom I
ſpake before <hi>Peter Wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> being himſelfe in danger, was ſaved
by the Mediation of the <hi>Lantgrave.</hi> Others of the Townſmen that were
good men, troubled at this to ſee that if they left the City they were forced
to run on preſent danger abroad, upon compulſion in a manner and againſt
their will, did ſtay behind.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:107072:17"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Community commanded. All bookes burnt but the Bible. A Smith
jeſts on them, and payes dearly for it.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ABout this time the <hi>fore-man</hi> of the <hi>Prophets</hi> (for
thats the Title they do arrogate unto themſelves) <hi>John Matthew</hi> gave
command that whatſoever Gold, ſilver, Moveables any man enjoyed, on paine
of death he ſhould bring forth among them. And for this Uſe there was a
publique houſe appointed. The people much amazed with the rigor of this
Order, Obey'd. Nor was it ſafe for any man to fayle, or to defraud them of
any part. For there were two Girles poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes'd with Spirits of Divination,
that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcovered whatſoever fraud had beene committed. Nor did they onely
bring their owne Goods thus together, but theirs alſo whom they had turned
out of Towne, they did convert to their owne uſe. This done, the ſelfe
ſame Prophet did command that no man henceforth keepe any other booke about 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107072:17"/>him but the holy Bible: all others muſt be brought forth
and aboliſhed. This was commanded, as he ſaid, from heaven. And thereupon
Books in great Number hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p'd together were all conſumed with fire. it
happened that a ſmith about that time, one <hi>Hubert Truteling</hi> had
broake ſome Jeſt upon the (ſelfe-named) Prophets, which being knowne they
call the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and command the Souldiers to be preſent: Inſtantly they
accuſe the fellow, and ſentence him to die. The people were exceedingly
aſtoniſhed at the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: But the fore-prophet (whom I nam'd
before) layes violent hands on the poore wretch, and with a ſpeare ſtabd
him lying flat on the ground: yet without Mortall wound, although he fell upon
him with a mighty force. Then he Commands him to be carried to another Place;
where ſnaching up a Gun, from a young man by him, with a Bullet ſhoots him
through, lying all along. The fellow for all this not dying preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he
tells them, <hi>that it was reveald from heaven unto him, that his time to dye
was not yet come, and God had ſhewne him mercy.</hi> But a few dayes after
the poore man ends his life. That being knowne <pb n="20" facs="tcp:107072:18"/>the Prophet,
all in haſt, catcheth up a long-ſized ſpeare, and running madly through
the City, <hi>Cryes out that God the Father had commanded him to beat off the
enemy from the City.</hi> Approaching to the Campe a certaine Souldier that
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him, ran him through. And though the error of his predictions was this
other time diſcovered alſo, yet had his Comrade Prophets ſo befool'd the
men and put ſo faire a dreſſe upon the buſineſſe, to the vulgar,
that he was much deſired, and ſome Calamity preſag'd impendent on them
from the loſſe of ſuch a <hi>Worthy perſonage.</hi> But <hi>John at
Leiden</hi> next Prophet to him bad them take heart, t'was long agoe reveal'd
to him that he ſhould come to ſuch an end. And for the wife he left, ſhe
ſhould be his. Within two daies of Eaſter they run into the Churches and
ſet all the Bells in every Place a ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Shortly after
<hi>Cnipperdoling</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyeth, <hi>That thoſe which were of the
higheſt forme muſt be tumbled downe, and others from the ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt bench and very dunghill be
exalted.</hi> Then bids he them demoliſh all the Churches, proteſting
ſeriouſly that he had ſuch command from God. They all are at his beck,
and with their utmoſt <pb n="21" facs="tcp:107072:18"/>diligence put in execution the
Command (he cals) from heaven. At the ſelfe ſame time almoſt <hi>Iohn at
Leiden</hi> gives the ſword to <hi>Cnipperdoling</hi> and makes him
<hi>Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> for ſuch was Gods pleaſure that <hi>He, before</hi> who
bare the greateſt office and was <hi>Confull, now</hi> take the meaneſt,
and be <hi>Hangman. He,</hi> far from unwilling, with thanks accepts the office
put upon him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. IX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The Biſhop craves aid of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Princes, and obtaines it.
The City ſtormed. But Without ſucceſse.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>WHen now the Biſhop for ſome Moneths had beene himſelfe at all
the Charge of war againſt them, <hi>Herman Archbiſhop of Colen,</hi> and
<hi>John Prince of Clev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſent
ayd of money, armes, and ſome troopes of horſe and foote. The Archbiſhop
of <hi>Colen</hi> goes alſo to the Campe himſelfe to give advice. And not
long after they aſſault the City in certaine Places. But when no hopes 
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:107072:19"/>remained of taking it by ſtorme, they built ſeven
fortreſſes to ſtop all Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and Place ſome Colours of foote,
and troops of horſe in every of them for winter quarters. And to the end the
ſiege and warre might be carryed on, which equally concern'd them all, the
<hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Munſter</hi> craves ayde of all the <hi>Princes</hi>
and the Cities in the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Rhene,</hi> as being next unto
him. For this, there was a meeting called at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence,</hi> about the
13th of <hi>December</hi> 1534. For Germany in the whole hath ſix
diviſions, <hi>Franconia, Bononia, Suevia, Saxony,</hi> the tract of
<hi>Rhene,</hi> and <hi>Burgundy.</hi> Within theſe limits of auncient
courſe were reckoned all the Princes and the Cities one or other at Imperiall
dyets. At this day is diviſion of the upper and the lower <hi>Saxony,</hi>
then alſo is there lower <hi>Germany, Weſtphalia</hi> and
<hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſo that at preſent tenne Countries doe make up the
Empire.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:107072:19"/>
            <head>CAP. X.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Leiden dreames three-dayes. Creates Twelve Governours. Propoſes
new Doctrins. Leading Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts ſeized by ſome well affected. Who
looſe their lives for it.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>AFter the fruitles ſtorme <hi>John a-Leiden</hi> takes him to his
reſt, and falls a drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming three whole dayes ſpace together. When he
awakes, ſpeaks not a word, but makes ſignes for paper, and therein
Aſſignes twelve men (ſome well deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Number) to be over all
affaires, and as in Iſraell, <hi>ſteere</hi> the whole. For this He
<hi>tells them is the heavenly</hi> Fathers <hi>pleaſure.</hi> And now, when
by the twelve a ſtirrup thus was made him to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he falls
propoſing certaine Tenets to the Preachers, and requires their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation
of them by the Scriptures: where if they fayld, he would referre them to the
People for their approbation, and eſtabliſhment. Of thoſe, this was the 
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:107072:20"/>Creame, <hi>That men were not obliged to one onely wife,
but if they pleaſed might marry many:</hi> which when their Teachers did
oppoſe, He calls them with the Twelve unto the hall. At their appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
there, he puts off his Cloake and threw it with a new Teſtament on the
ground; by thoſe as ſignes he ſweares, <hi>The Doctrine he had broached,
was revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from heaven to him,</hi> &amp; therefore ſharply threatens
them, with the frownes of God upon them, if they do not bid it welcome.</p>
            <p>At laſt <hi>they jumpe,</hi> and it was a full three daies worke
for the Preachers Sermons to talke of Marriage. He quickly gets him three
wives, one, the great Prophets <hi>John Mathew,</hi> of whom I ſpeake before.
This leading caſe others were not long behind So as t'was reckoned for a
credit to be often married. But now ſome Citizens that could by no meanes
brooke this trade, by a token given through the City get all that loved the
Goſpell to a meeting at the Hall. Then they lay hold upon the <hi>Prophet.
Cnipperdoling,</hi> and all the <hi>Teachers.</hi> The Rable at firſt notice
of it run to Armes, reſcue the Priſoners, and with cruell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſlew
ſome fifty: for tying ſome <pb n="25" facs="tcp:107072:20"/>to Trees and ſtakes they
ſhot them through: The ring-leading Prophet making acclamation, <hi>That he
that would do God good ſervice ſhould diſcharge upon them firſt.</hi>
Others had other ends.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> A new prophet declares that John a-Leiden muſt be King. Tis
done. Cnipperdoling playing Rex is put in priſon.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ABout the 24 fourth of Juneup ſtarts a new Prophet by trade a
Goldſmith. He having cal'd the People to the Hall, declare it as the will and
pleaſure of the heavenly father, <hi>that John a-Leiden ſhould be Lord of
all the world, and that he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching forthwith a mighty Army ſhould deſtroy
all Kings and Princes, one or other, ſhewing mercy to the People only, that
is, to thoſe that do love righteouſneſſe: and that he ſhould
poſſeſſe the ſeat of his father David, untill the Father do require
the Kingdome of him, for the ungodly troden under foote, the Saints muſt
raigne, even in this <pb n="26" facs="tcp:107072:21"/>life.</hi> This ſpoken openly,
<hi>John a-Leiden</hi> inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly faling on his knees and lifting up his
hands to heaven cries out, <hi>Men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I have beene no ſtranger to
this buſineſſe, for theſe many daies, and yet I had no mind to
publiſh it, but now, to put it out of doubt, the Father hath made uſe of
another Meſſenger.</hi> Thus being then made King he forthwith Nulls the
Twelve, and as the Regall mode is, <hi>Creates him Nobles, Commands two
Crownes, a Scabbard, Chaine, &amp; Scepter with other ſuch like Badges of
ſtate to be provided for him</hi> of the pureſt Gold. Then he appointed
certaine daies of hearing in all cauſes that required his Cognizance. As
often as he came in Publique he was attended with his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and nobles of
his Court. Next to him followed too young men mounted. He on the right with a
Crowne and Bible, the other with a naked ſword. In like ſtate was his
Principall wife attended, for he had many at that time: In the hall there was
erected a lofty throne of ſtate, covered with Cloth of Gold. The Complaints
and ſuits before him, for the moſt part were of marrying or divorcing, a
thing now thredbare with them. Inſomuch that <pb n="27" facs="tcp:107072:21"/>ſome who
many yeares had lived toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were now firſt put aſunder. But on a time
the People ſtanding very thick and crowded in the hall to heare, Loe,
<hi>Cnipperdoling</hi> leapeth up and Scrabling by all foure on the Crowd, he
wanders to and fro upon their Tops, and gaping wide mouthed on them, ſaith to
them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, <hi>The Father hath Sanctified thee, receive the Holy
Ghoſt.</hi> Another day leading a dance before the King, quoth he, <hi>thus
my litle whore and I ſometimes are want to do: But now the Father bad me do
the ſame before the King.</hi> And when he never would have done, the King
went forth offended at him. Then he mounts up the throne and <hi>Playes
Rex</hi> himſelfe. But the King the while returning puls downe my man and
claps him three dayes up in priſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:107072:22"/>
            <head>CAP. XII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> A booke Printed for the Raigne of Saints. And confuted.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe ſiege continuing they write a booke&amp;publiſh it, their
Title is <hi>The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</hi> Herein, with other ſtuffe, they broach:
<hi>That Chriſts kingdome ſhall be ſuch before the laſt day of
Judgment, that all the ungodly every where extinct, the Godly and the Elect
ſhall raigne.</hi> They tell us alſo, that the people may turne off their
Magiſtrates, <hi>and though the Apoſtles were not commanded to take the
Civill power into their hands, yet the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſters of the Church
ought to clayme title to the Sword, and to enforce a new forme of Government.
Moreover, that none but true Chriſtians might be ſuffered in the Church,
and that none could be ſaved except they would relinquish all propriety in
the Eſtate they had, and make it common. For</hi> Luther <hi>and the</hi>
Pope <hi>of</hi> Rome <hi>they were both</hi> falſe Prophets, <hi>yet Luther
was the worſer of the twaine. And as to</hi> unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers <pb n="29" facs="tcp:107072:22"/>Marriage, <hi>tis polluted and impure, nor to be reckoned</hi> (ſay
they) <hi>than for whoredome and adultery.</hi> Thoſe their opinions were
oppugned chiefely by <hi>Melancthon, Juſtus, Menius,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus
Rhegius</hi> whoſe writings upon this Subject are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant very cleere and
full.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> New Apoſtles. Their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>A few weekes after the new-ſprung Prophet Spoken of before, by
Sound of Trumpet throughout all the Streets proclaimes <hi>that all ſhould
make appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in their Armes at the Cathedrall-Porch,</hi> becauſe <hi>the
enemy muſt be ſent pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Citie.</hi> At their coming thither
they find a ſupper ready. Being bad about 4000 ſit downe unto it: after,
they ſup that were the while upon the guard about 1000. The <hi>King</hi> and
<hi>Queene</hi> with their houſhold Servants wait. Having eaten and ſupper
almoſt ended, the King himſelfe reaching bread to every one ſaith,
<hi>Take eat ſhew forth the <pb n="30" facs="tcp:107072:23"/>death of the Lord:</hi> The
Queene holding out the cup ſaith, <hi>Drink, and ſhew forth the death of
the Lord.</hi> This done the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Prophet ſteps up into a pulpit,
askes them whether they would obey the word of God: All ſaying, <hi>yea,</hi>
quoth he, <hi>It is the fathers command that Teachers of the word ſhould be
ſent forth, about eight and twenty, who going into the foure quarters of the
world may preach the doctrine famous in this City.</hi> Then names he them,
directs the way that every one ſhould take. Six were diſpatched to
<hi>Oſenbruge,</hi> as many unto <hi>Warendorſe,</hi> eight unto
<hi>Suſat,</hi> the like number unto <hi>Cosfield.</hi> Afterwards the King
and Queene ſit downe to ſupper with their other ſervants, and thoſe
appointed for the progreſſe. At ſupper the king ſtarts up: ſayes,
that he hath a litle buſineſſe the father hath commanded. It chanced
there was a certaine Souldier taken him, as another <hi>Judas,</hi> the King
accuſed of treaſon and himſelfe beheads him. This done he returned to
ſupper, and merily brags of that his brave exploit. Having ſup'd the
foreſaid 28 are ſent away, within night a litle, and beſides proviſions
for <pb n="31" facs="tcp:107072:23"/>their journy every man hath his peece of Gold which in
the places where their doctrine is refuſed they are bid to leave behind them,
as a token of their future deſtruction and eternall ruine, for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of
peace, and ſuch a ſaving doctrine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. V.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The Apoſtles behaviour. And enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement where they
come.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>WHen they departing came into their ſeverall places, with a loud
out cry through the ſtreets. <hi>That men repent, or looke for ſuddaine
ruine:</hi> They ſpread their garments on the ground be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the
magiſtrate, and threw the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den peeces that they had receiv'd thereon,
<hi>aſſuring them that the father ſent them to offer peace unto them,
which if they would imbrace, they muſt make common what they had, but if they
did refuſe, then hereby, as an earneſt, they did proteſt againſt this
wickedneſſe of theirs and ingratitude. For now the time is come whereof all
the <pb n="32" facs="tcp:107072:24"/>Prophets ſpake, when through all the world God will
have righteouſneſſe be embraced. And when the</hi> King <hi>in doing of
this dutie ſhall bring the buſineſſe unto ſuch a paſſe that
righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe raigne in every place, then ſhall it be that Chriſt
deliver up the Kingdome to his father.</hi> Talking at this rate they are laid
hold off, and freindly firſt, then on the rack examin'd of their faith and
life, and of the Cities Strength. They anſwer, <hi>that only they
themſelves held the true Doctrine and they would beare witneſſe to it at
the perill of their lives. For from the very Apoſtles time neither had the
word of God beene truly taught, nor any righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſet a foot.
There are in all foure Prophets, and no more, two righteous ones,</hi> David
<hi>and</hi> John a-Leiden, <hi>two wicked, the</hi> Pope <hi>and</hi> Luther,
<hi>and</hi> this the worſer of the twaine. Being asked why againſt their
promiſe given they baniſhed honeſt men the City, ſeizing on their goods
and wives; and Children, and by what place of Scripture could they prove and
maintaine that righteouſneſſe of theirs. They ſay, this is the time
Chriſt ſpake of, <hi>that the meeke ſhould inherit the earth, and in this
manner heretofore God gave the Egyptians goods unto the Iſralites.</hi>
Speaking after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <pb n="33" facs="tcp:107072:24"/>of the forces and proviſions of the
citie, they confeſſe, <hi>moſt men have above five wives and that they
looked for forces out of</hi> Friezland <hi>and from</hi> Holland, <hi>as
ſoone as ere they come, the King will march forth with all his Army and
ſubdue the world unto himſelfes putting to death the Kings for not
adminiſtring Juſtice.</hi> Having beene examined, when they would bide by
what they were, nor acknowledge any Magiſtrate beſides their King, Death
was their doome, yet one of them eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The King makes Dukes, and Halbaltiers. Their Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>BY this, the City was ſo cloſe begirt that there was no way of
getting out for any: the Citizens therefore fearing famine and troubled at the
danger they <pb n="34" facs="tcp:107072:25"/>were in, had thoughts to apprehend the King and
deliver him bound unto the Biſhop. The King, that by ſome tokens Smelt the
buſineſſe out, makes choice of twelve out of all the heap, that he judged
moſt faithfull, and calls them <hi>Dukes,</hi> aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning unto every of
them ſome part of the City to defend: and alſo yeomen of the Guard to
prevent commotions. Then did he promiſe all the people that at Eaſter they
ſhould be quit both of Siege and want together. But for the <hi>Dukes</hi> he
choſe, far greater matters are aſſured to them: they ſhall be
<hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> (as he tells them) yea and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
layes out, what <hi>Province, Caſtles,</hi> and <hi>Mannors</hi> each
ſhould have. None but the <hi>Lantgrave</hi> ſhould be ſpared, he ſaid;
becauſe he hoped at laſt <hi>he</hi> would ſtrike in with him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:107072:25"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> More Princes meet. The beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged admoniſhed.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>ABove we told you of a meeting called at <hi>Confluence</hi> in the
month December, of thoſe ſtates that were with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Province of
<hi>Rhene,</hi> with them aſſociated of his owne accord <hi>John Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick
Prince Elector</hi> of <hi>Saxony.</hi> The buſineſſe duly weighed in
that aſſembly, ſpeedy aydes are ordered to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> of
horſe three-hundred, and three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand foot for ſix months ſpace.
Over theſe forces and the whole warre <hi>Wirich</hi> Earle of
<hi>Oberſtene</hi> is made Generall. 'Tis ordered alſo that all other
ſtates within the Empire ſhall be ſollicited for aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. And
becauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> was in Spaine that King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> be
deſired againſt Aprill next for this to call a <hi>Dyet.</hi> Then ſent
they letters ſharply <hi>to admoniſh the beſieged to leave off their
courſe, which is ſo both diſhoneſt and ungodly as nothing more: except
they yeild and ſubmit them to their <pb n="36" facs="tcp:107072:26"/>lawfull Magiſtrate,
they tell them plainly that the whole Empire will not be wanting to
aſſiſt the</hi> Biſhop. This was about Decembers end. They anſwere
the 13th day of January 1535. with words enough, but litle to the purpoſe.
Yet ſo as too commend and juſtifie their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takement, but as to what had
beene ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected about the King they coyned, they are quite dumb to that.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XVII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Anabaptiſts write to the Lantgrave. The Anſwers. They Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
&amp;c.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>BUt in their private letters to the <hi>Lantgrave</hi> they would
faine excuſe themſelves, talking much about <hi>the ruine and deſtruction
of all the wicked, about the liberty and dominion of the godly in this
life,</hi> and herewith ſend him the booke of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> that I
ſpake of. They admoniſh him alſo to <hi>repent and not like other
Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wicked men, wage warre againſt <pb n="37" facs="tcp:107072:26"/>them
harmleſſe ſoules, and Gods people.</hi> The <hi>Lantgrave</hi> having
read the <hi>Letter</hi> and the <hi>booke</hi> notes what he did diſlike
therein, and orders ſome of his to anſwer. And ſince they very briefely
but ſomewhat blindly wrote, their king was not ſo much of theirs, as of
Gods appointment. He askes them <hi>why they did not ſhew thoſe Scriptures
whence they thought this courſe was lawfull, and why they had not firſt
confirmed it by ſignes and wonders. For of</hi> Chriſts <hi>coming</hi> God
<hi>by all his</hi> Prophets <hi>long before foretold ſo evidently that not
only of what tribe or ſtock, but alſo when and where he ſhould be borne
was cleerely mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt.</hi> Twas alſo their deſire to have a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of
their cauſe. Hereto the <hi>Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> anſweres. <hi>Now there was no
roome for that ſince they had uſurped authority and were the Authors of
ſo much miſchiefe. For all men ſee whereat they ayme, even to the
overthrowing lawes and common-wealths. And as their courſe is palpably wicked
and villanous, ſo alſo the deſire of having cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance taken of their
Cauſe is faigned and counterfeit. That for his part he had ſent them
faithfull miniſters of the Church, by whom he is ſure, they have beene well
inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. But whereas by their naſty doctrine <pb n="38" facs="tcp:107072:27"/>they</hi> revolt from their Magiſtrate, Seize on other mens
eſtates, take many wives, chuſe a new King, deny Chriſt to have taken
humane nature of the Virgin Mary, aſſert free will, force men to make all
common, deny forgiveneſſe to a lapſed ſinner. <hi>Theſe all are both
againſt the lawes of God and men.</hi> This anſwer brought them, they fall
againe to ſcribling, and ſend withall a booke compoſed in the vulgar
ſpeech, <hi>Of Scripture Myſteries.</hi> In their Epiſtle, they put new
trimming on their cauſe, and reinforce their principles: but in the booke we
ſpeake of they divide the whole worlds age, from firſt to laſt into three
periods, &amp; the firſt (they tell us) <hi>from</hi> Adam <hi>unto</hi> Noah
<hi>periſhed by a floud, the other wherein we are ſhall by fire, the third
ſhall be new all over,</hi> wherein reigneth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. <hi>But
before this laſt appeare, the preſent muſt be changed with fire. Yet
that's not like to be till Antichriſt be revealed, and his power quite
ſubdued. Then ſhall it be that the decayed throne of</hi> David <hi>ſhall
be erected, and</hi> Chriſt obtaine his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the earth, <hi>and all
the writings of the</hi> Prophets <hi>he fulfilled. For the preſent world is
as the age of</hi> Eſau, <hi>for both herein is juſtice ſilenced, and the
godly are afflicted. But <pb n="39" facs="tcp:107072:27"/>as from</hi> Babylons
<hi>captivity, ſo alſo now from ſo great miſeries the time of</hi>
deliverance and reſtoring <hi>is at hand: and the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the
wicked ſhall be abundantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced to them, as is ſignified in
the</hi> Revelation. <hi>But this</hi> reſtoring <hi>ſhall precede the
world to come, that all ungodly men trod under foot, a ſeat and habitation
may be prepared for righteouſneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Lantgrave</hi> having
received their booke commends it to ſome Miniſters of the Church with him
to draw up the confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XVIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Free Cities meet at Eſling. The Reſult.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe decree that was made at <hi>Conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> ſome few cities
that were preſent utterly diſliked, and ſay they will ſend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice home
againſt it. After, all the other cities of the <hi>Empire</hi> meete at
<hi>Eſling:</hi> and there they come to this Concluſion, <hi>that they who
met before at</hi> Confluence <hi>had not to do to impoſe any charge on them:
for that therein there ought to be the</hi> Authority <pb n="40" facs="tcp:107072:28"/>
               <hi>and</hi> Conſent <hi>of</hi> Caeſar <hi>and all the ſtates.
Therefore they reject that Order made, and promiſe mutuall helpe in caſe
that any danger be incur'd in that regard by any of them. But whatſoever
ſhall be duly reſolved upon for publique good in publique</hi> Diets <hi>of
the</hi> Empire, <hi>therein they give aſſurance they will do their
duty.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XIX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> City wants proviſion. One of the Queenes pitties the poore. The
King beheads her for it. And promiſes largely to the people, but payes
poorely.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>BUt now proviſions growing ſo ſcarce and deare throughout the
citie in the moneth of <hi>February,</hi> that there was no hopes but ſome
muſt needs be <hi>hunger-ſtarved:</hi> one of the <hi>Queenes</hi>
commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the peoples caſe did chance to ſay unto the others,
<hi>that ſhe did not think it was the will of God, to have the people thus
conſumed with famine.</hi> The <hi>King,</hi> 
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:107072:28"/>whoſe
<hi>Larder</hi> was well fraught not only for <hi>neceſſity</hi> but even
to <hi>luxury,</hi> hearing hereof brings her and all the other with her to the
Hall. Where having bade her fall upon her knees, <hi>he takes off her
head,</hi> and being dead, <hi>brands her for a whore.</hi> Upon this deed, the
other chaunt his praiſe and <hi>thanke the heavenly father.</hi> The king
then leades a round, and perſwades the people that had nothing left but
<hi>bread</hi> and <hi>ſalt</hi> to <hi>dance</hi> and to be <hi>merry.</hi>
But when <hi>Eaſter</hi> came and no deliverance did appeare: The
<hi>King</hi> that had beene <hi>Laviſh of his promiſe,</hi> to ſalve the
buſineſſe feignes himſelfe ſick for ſix dayes ſpace, at laſt
comes forth into the Hall, and tells them, <hi>He had ſate upon a blinde
Aſſe, and that the father had laid the ſins of all the people on his
back, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were cleane all over, nor needed any other expiation.
This was that deliverance which he promiſed, wherewith they ought to be
content.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:107072:29"/>
            <head>CAP. XX.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi> Luther</hi> writes againſt the Anabaptiſts.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ther,</hi> amongſt other things he put forth at this time
in the country <hi>Language, Alas! quoth he, what or how ſhall I complaine
and bemoane thoſe wretched creatures? In truth the thing it ſelfe doth
ſay that</hi> Devils <hi>dwell</hi> in heapes <hi>among them. But for our
parts we have all reaſon in the world highly to advance Gods bottomleſſe
mercy. For notwithſtanding</hi> for contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Goſpell, and
reproaching of the name of God, <hi>and</hi> powring forth the blood of godly
men, <hi>Germany deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ſore affliction at the hands of God: yet has he
curbed hitherto</hi> Sathans <hi>rage and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and doth not lay the reine
upon his neck to let him rant it at his pleaſure with us; but is a
gentle</hi> Monitor, <hi>and by this</hi> Munſter <hi>tragedy (far from a
cunning peece) calls us to amendment. For ſhould not God bridle and check him
in, I make no queſtion but</hi> that moſt ſubtill ſpirit, <hi>and</hi>
ſuch a maſter of his craft <hi>would have managed matters at a far other
rate. But now ſince God hath <pb n="43" facs="tcp:107072:29"/>maimed him ſorely, he
ſtormes and rageth, not how himſelfe deſireth, and would have it, but as
the rope is given him. For that wicked ſpirit which endeavors to ſubvert
the Chriſtian faith, takes not this courſe to</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce polygamy,
<hi>becauſe, ſince all men ſee the curſed baſeneſſe of the
thing,</hi> he knows <hi>it well enough, they will abhor it. Policy indeed and
civill government may be this way diſturbed, but</hi> Chriſts kingdome
<hi>muſt with other tooles and engines be aſſaulted. He that will neatly
toll a man into deceit and ſnares, muſt not put ſtrait for a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
or dominion, and</hi> play the Tyrant. <hi>For all men do condemne that
courſe and ſee his aymes. But by ſome hidden meanes as foot-paths come
unto it. To weare a</hi> ruſty garbe <hi>thats out of faſhion, to</hi>
ſet ones face to gravity, <hi>to</hi> hang downe the head, <hi>to</hi>
faſt, <hi>to</hi> touch no money, <hi>to</hi> eat no fleſh, <hi>to</hi>
abhorre marriage, <hi>to reckon</hi> civill office <hi>or</hi> Magiſtracy
<hi>as</hi> prophane, <hi>to</hi> refuſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>to</hi> profeſſe
a ſingular humility of mind: <hi>here lyes the way, and</hi> Method <hi>to
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap a wiſe man by, and that doth by diſguiſe, and in the darke ſet
ope the dore to</hi> Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty. <hi>But by a</hi> face of braſſe <hi>to
claime a kingdome, to take as many wives as his luſt inclines him to, this is
not the ſubtilty of an</hi> 
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:107072:30"/>artificiall Divell, <hi>but
ſome one</hi> newly at the trade. <hi>Or if he be the</hi> Maſter of his
Craft, <hi>for certaine then God hath ſo tyed his hands that he cannot play
his game more cunningly. The end whereof no doubt is that we might feare his
Majeſtie, and be ſtirred up to repentance before he looſe that</hi>
beaten Souldier <hi>which ſurely will aſſault us much more to our damage.
For if a</hi> young Gramarian Divell <hi>can make ſuch ſtirs, what will
they be, when he comes full ſayle againſt us as an</hi> higher graduat,
<hi>I meane as</hi> Lawyer or Divine? <hi>Such a rude Divell therefore neede
not much affright us.</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>And I alſo thinke this</hi> trifling ſtage-play <hi>likes
not all thoſe in the city, but very many have ſad harts about it who not
without ſighes and teares waite for Gods deliverance: as ſome yeares
ſince it proved in the inſurrection of the country men. And would to God
there was no</hi> craftier Divell <hi>in the world than this of</hi> Munſter.
<hi>Let God but ſpare his word among us, in truth I am perſwaded that
ſcarce a man would heede ſuch a</hi> homely ſenſeleſſe ſir.
<hi>Although indeed when the wrath of God is kindled, there is no errour ſo
abſurd and graceleſſe but Sathan can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade it, as we ſee befell
in the doctrine for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">This fellow was an
<hi>Arabian,</hi> of the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> borne meanly a out the year of Chriſt <hi>597,</hi>
his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was a <hi>Pagan,</hi> his mother a <hi>Jew,</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of
<hi>no religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> In his youth he ſerved a Merchant and kept his camels.
His maſter dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; by the help of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick</hi> he married his Miſtris,
left very rich. Being a crafty fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious, yet no ſchollar he
makes himſelfe a <hi>prophet,</hi> pretends revelations, goes up and downe
amongſt his country men awretched people, never under any good government,
but either lived at home by robbery, or elſe were ſoulders of fortune
abroad and ſetting his fancies to their lioeptious humours gets many
followers. In fits of the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, frequent with him, he made
believe the <hi>Angell Gabriel</hi> converſed with him, which his fleſh not
able to beare fainted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Another of his taking cheats was that a dove
being taught to feich corne at his eare paſſed currant for the holy ghoſt
revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling myſteries to him. Thus getting famous, the <hi>Saracens</hi> his
countrimen who fought under <hi>Heraclius the Emperor</hi> being denyed their
pay and cal'd dogs for asking it, revolt, o're whom with litle difficulty
<hi>Mahomet</hi> is made generall about the yeare <hi>620.</hi> Then to make
ſure, by the helpe of ſome beretiques and Jewes, he compiles a forme of
Doctrine, called the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> which is the peoples Bible and ſweares
the <hi>Angell Gabriel</hi> carried him to heaven and there he learnt it. Some
other things be taught them. In truth his doctrine is a very monſter patched
up with ſcraps of <hi>Chriſtianity, Judaiſme</hi> and
<hi>Paganiſme</hi> cramb'd with non-ſenſe fables and ſelfe
contradictions. For a taſt of all. <hi>That Chriſt was a great Prophet (not
God) but Mahomet greater. The Jewes did not crucify him, but one like him.
Children muſt be circumciſed. Ofterings made in the Temple at</hi> Mecca.
<hi>Turne thitherwardin all their prayers. God in</hi> Sinay <hi>(as in one
place, but elſewhere tis in Hieruſalem) gave 1515 precepts.</hi> Noah
<hi>deſired God to drowne the world for the Idols of</hi> Huden Scbuon Jaguta
Jannea Naccu <hi>Tis lawfull to have foure wives and as many Concubines as one
pleaſe. The Angel</hi> Gabriel <hi>flying his wing chanced to touch the Moone
and darkned it. The day of Judgment Continues 50000 years. After it Death
ſhall be turned into a ram. Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe conſiſt in ſenſuall
pleaſures, faire women &amp;c. Hundreds more as bad</hi> [Magdeb. Cent.
<hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi> See Alcoran in Engliſh.] yet are the Turks by far
the vaſteſt Empire in the worll, bewitched with this Vanity at this very
day. Whether Muncer, Leiden and too many of the preſent time with us came not
out of <hi>Mathomets ſhop</hi> I referre to the Readers owne
Reſolution.</note> Mahomet.</q> 
               <hi>For though <pb facs="tcp:107072:30"/>there be not one
drame of braines in any rag</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:107072:31"/> 
               <q>
                  <hi>thereof or the whole peace together:</hi> Yet the light of
Scripture being out, it ſpread ſo far, and grew to ſuch a pitch as now we
ſee it.</q> Which, had not <hi>Muncers</hi> counſels and endeavors beene
cruſhed by God, would have beene the ſame in Germany. For the <hi>leaſt
ſparke</hi> 
               <q>that is when God gives leave, Sathan can blow into a <hi>mighty
flame.</hi>
               </q> Nor is there any better way to quench this fire than by the
word of God. For whereas 
<q>the enemy weareth not corporall armes he cannot be conquered by
either troops of horſe or any other warlike engines.</q> But our Princes and
our Biſhops goe another way to worke. 
<q>They hinder the <hi>Goſpels teaching,</hi> whereby alone the
minds and hearts of men are healed; and try the while to ſave by
puniſhments the body from the Divell, but the better part of man his very
heart and ſoule they let him take. They ſpeed herein juſt as the
<hi>Jewes</hi> that would extinguiſh <hi>Chriſt</hi> by croſſe and
puniſhment.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q>But now as to the things that are ſpoke abroad, and written of
the men of <hi>Munſter.</hi> I take them to be very truthes.</q> And I am
confirmed herein by their owne writing lately publiſhed. <pb n="47" facs="tcp:107072:31"/>

               <q>wherein their madneſſe is neatly pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by themſelves. For
firſt in <hi>matters of faith,</hi> they teach very fowle abſurdities. And
of Chriſt, as if he were not fowen Of Mary (as they phraſe it) although
they do confeſſe that he came of the ſeed of <hi>David.</hi> But they do
not fully let us know their mind herein.</q> The Devill hatcheth (ſure
enough) ſome mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter under it. Tis true this is not darkly hinted by him,
That the ſeed or fleſh of Mary cannot ſave us. But the attempt 
<q>is fruitleſſe, for Scripture ſpeakes it, that <hi>Chriſt
was borne of the Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> which phraſe all languages do referre to
a young one that, conceived and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the mothers fleſh and blood, is
brought to light.</q>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q>Then for their cenſure on <hi>former bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> as
prophane: that alſo is their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. For they do not reckon it as an
ordinance of God, but as a worke of man.</q> But if that ought to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
wholy, and throwne out of doores 
<q>whatſoever wicked men do give or have</q>, I wonder truly why
they do not abhorre the Gold and ſilver and other riches </p>
            <q> 
               <p>which they robbed from the wicked; and invent new ſubſtance for
themſelves, <pb n="48" facs="tcp:107072:32"/>for, as theſe things, ſo alſo
baptiſme is the worke and creature of God. When a wicked man ſweareth he
abuſeth the true name of God; if it be not the true name of God to him, he
doth not ſin. He that robbeth by the way, ſtealeth, or makes a prey of any
thing, breaketh the command of God: if it be not the true command of God to
him, he offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not. So alſo if our former bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme be null, then they
who were by it baptiz'd did not amiſſe. Why then do they accurſe the
former baptiſme as a peece of villany, <hi>when yet tis nothing by their owne
ſaying.</hi>
               </p> 
               <p> If marriages of the former age be to be reckoned as whoredome and
adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; becauſe contracted betweene thoſe, they ſay, that wanted faith
pray do they not confeſſe themſelves to be the ſons of whores? Now if
they be baſtards and illegittimate tell me why do they hold the
poſſeſſions of their cities, and their Anceſtors? In truth it were
but meete, ſince they are ſuch, to diſ-inherit them, and with their new
kind of marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, turne them to get new riches and eſtates of an honeſter
title. Nor truly is it handſome for ſuch holy and foreſooth <pb facs="tcp:107072:32"/>religious men to ſupport their lives with theſe whoriſh
illegitimate goods, or take them by force and robbery from other men. As to
that their <hi>ridiculous kingdome:</hi> there are therein ſo many and ſuch
palpable peeces of roguery that I neede not ſay a word more to it.</p>
            </q>
            <p> And truly this we ſpeake is both too much, 
<q>and ſeemes not very neceſſary, ſpecially ſince others
fully have diſpatched the ſame already.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XXI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi> A</hi> Dyet <hi>held at</hi> Wormes.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN the Diet of the empire, which king <hi>Ferdinand</hi> at the
intreaty of the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> did by his<note n="(a)" place="margin">Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors or Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> 
               <hi>Legates</hi>
appoint at <hi>Wormes</hi> in the month of Aprill, the Cities, which had
hitherto parted with no monies, at their firſt entrance do proteſt that
their appearance there was not for the order made at <hi>Confluence</hi> but in
obedience unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>King Ferdinand.</hi> Then fell they to
great daſhing with them about the contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Princes. At laſt
they did <pb facs="tcp:107072:33"/>conclude of ayde for five Months ſpace, at the rate of
20000 Crownes the month: alſo that the Citie being got by ſtorme or
otherwiſe there ſhould be mercy ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the harmeleſſe Multitude:
&amp; that the honeſt, who either were beſieged or had wandered to ſome
other place ſhould have their goods reſtored to them. Upon this order the
<hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Munſter</hi> gives up the <hi>Armie</hi> to
<hi>Oberſtene.</hi> But whereas publique monies were very ſlow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and
almoſt too late diſpatched unto them, nothing worthy notice could be
at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheived; yea the Captaines more than once were in danger of their lives by
the Souldiers mutiny for want of pay.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:107072:33"/>
            <head>CAP. XXII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The famine increaſeth. Many die. The reſt complaine. But hold
on their courſe.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>NOw when within the city things were in ſuch a plight that many
daily periſhed with the famine: many alſo got away to other places, who
came forth, <hi>ſo nothing elſe but very skin and bone,</hi> that it
commanded pitty from <hi>the enemy</hi> to them: the commanders give the
Towneſ-men notice if they would deliver but the <hi>King</hi> &amp; ſome
few others with him, <hi>themſelves ſhould ſuffer nothing.</hi> The
Citizens, though it were their earneſt longing, yet frighted by the
vigilancy, and ſeverity of the <hi>King</hi> durſt not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For ſo
obſtinate was the King that whilſt he lived as himſelfe (but with
fewothers) openly declared he would never yeeld. The Commanders therefore upon
this writing back forbid the ſending forth of any more, <hi>ſo much as
women and Children.</hi> This was the firſt day of <pb n="52" facs="tcp:107072:34"/>June.
Next day they anſwere, complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that they could not have a lawfull
hearing, and that they were ill dealt with, <hi>far beſide their merit,</hi>
in the ſoareſt manner: that if any would diſcover their errour to them,
they ſhould be ready to their duty. Then they unfold a place of
<hi>Daniel</hi> about the fourth beaſt, which was by far the cruelleſt of
them all. <hi>The cloſe of the letter was by Gods bleſſing they would
abide by this confeſſion of the truth.</hi> But all this was thus written
by the Kings appointment.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XXIII.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Two Revolters ſuggeſt a way to take the City. Their
counſell embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. And the City taken. Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans deſperate end. The King
and Cnipperdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling taken Priſoners.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>BUt now when things within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie were brought unto the loweſt
ebbe, out ran <hi>two of them.</hi> One taken by the Souldiers, the other, upon
paroll <pb n="53" facs="tcp:107072:34"/>comes to the Biſhop, and both tell the way to take
the City. <hi>Oberſtene</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop</hi> having heard the
revolters talke, and the buſineſſe duly weighed, on June the 22 by parle
adviſe the towneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to yeeld themſelves, and ſave the ſtarving
multitude. They in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the King, anſwer by <hi>Rotman:</hi>
yet ſo as to hold on their courſe. Two dayes after about eleven a clock by
night the forces drew downe ſilently to the Citie, and by the induſtry of
one of thoſe revolted, the forlorn having ſlaine the centineſs, get
thorow the trench into the bulwark: others at their heeles find a wicket open,
and about five hundred with ſome captaines and their collours threſt
through into the City. There then the towneſmen in a body made others halt
that were breaking in at laſt with much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe repulſe them, and clapping
faſt the gate fall on thoſe gat in allready, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting many to the ſword.
And when a ſharpe diſpute held thus for two houres ſpace, the Souldiers
thus ſhut in teare up by ſtrength of hand the gate next to them, where the
guard was weake, and cleere an entrance for their fellowes, who inſtantly
ruſh in with a mighty Ocean. <pb n="54" facs="tcp:107072:35"/>And when at firſt the
towneſmen ſtood their ground, and had made good the Hall; the caſe
appearing deſperate, and many ſlaine; they, at the firſt aſſault
<hi>cry quarter</hi> and <hi>obtaine</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Here now the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Cnipper doling</hi> both are
taken priſoners. <hi>Rotman</hi> paſt hopes of eſcaping, that he might
not fall into their hands alive, Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the enemies body and is ran through.
The city being taken, halfe the plunder and the Armes the <hi>Biſhop</hi>
taketh to himſelfe. Then the Army is disbanded: two Collours only kept to be
his guard.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:107072:35"/>
            <head>CAP. XXIV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> Another <hi>Dyet</hi> of the Empire.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THere followes upon this another Diet of the Empire at
<hi>Wormes</hi> about the 15 day of July. Therein King <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> by
his Legates doth propoſe and aske whether, <hi>the Citie being now
poſſeſſed, courſe ſhould be farther taken for the utter rooting out
of the Anabaptiſts. Adviſeth alſo, that the Princes move the</hi> Pope
<hi>about the Counſell.</hi> They anſwere, <hi>what courſe to take with
Anabaptiſts is provided for allready by certaine Edicts. For a counſell
the</hi> Pope <hi>hath more than once beene ſolicited thereunto by Caeſar:
nor would they make, they ſaid, any further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe in it.</hi> At the
ſame meeting the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> deſireth that his charge
and dammage might be repaired; and complaineth that the monies promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed were
not yet come in. When no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings farther could be had, and few
<hi>Eſtates</hi> were preſent, another meeting was appointed about the
firſt day of November, when there ſhould be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring had of the accounts
and charges of the warre: and reſolved upon what forme of government for the
time to come at <pb n="56" facs="tcp:107072:36"/>
               <hi>Munſter</hi> ſhould be
eſtabliſhed. When that day came, the Legate of <hi>King Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi>
reports the cauſes of the calling this Aſſembly, namely among other
things, <hi>that it might be alſo thought on how the Citie lately taken might
be hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſetled in its old Religion.</hi> Then the Biſhops legate
ſhewes them how <hi>great expences he was at throughout the war, how deepely
he was run in debt, how, though the Citie now were taken, yet to prevent
diſturbance and all danger he was enforced to raiſe two Cittadels in the
City and to gariſon them:</hi> Upon all which he deſireth conſideration
may be taken. T'was anſwered: that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> was
poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed <hi>allready of both the greater part of the ſpoiles and
all the Armes, yea, and the</hi> Citizens <hi>goods, all which indeede belong
unto the Empire: that it was meet to have the things, being prized, compared
with the charge, what more was wanting care ſhould be had thereof.</hi> After
twas reſolved that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Munſter,</hi> as
heretofore, ſhould be ſubject to the Empiretall the <hi>Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> he
reſtored, and the <hi>Citizens</hi> alſo, ſo they were not
<hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> that were wandered unto other places: for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> follow the decrees <pb n="57" facs="tcp:107072:36"/>of the
Empire, in the beginning of the ſpring, next yeare that the <hi>Legates</hi>
of the <hi>Princes</hi> go to <hi>Munſter,</hi> take Cognizance of the
Citizens conditions, ſave the innocent, demoliſh all the forts raiſed by
the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, and that the Biſhop alſo pull downe the Cittadels
raiſed by himſelfe within the Citie. For the <hi>King</hi> and
<hi>Cnipperdoling</hi> and <hi>Cretchting,</hi> that were priſoners, let him
puniſh them without longer ſtay at the firſt opportunity ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to
their demerits. As to that we told you was reſolved on about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the
Princes of <hi>Saxony,</hi> the <hi>Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> of <hi>VVirtemberg,</hi>
and <hi>Anhalt</hi> publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quely proteſted their diſſent the ſame
profeſſed the Cities alſo: and they would not have the ancient
fortifications of the City to be demoliſhed, for the new they were
content.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:107072:37"/>
            <head>CAP. XV.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The King and his fellow priſoners carryed about to the Princes.
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates with them.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe <hi>King</hi> and his two fellow priſoners were carried up and
downe unto the Princes to be looked, and laughed at; Through this occaſion
the <hi>Lantgraves</hi> Preachers get a conference with the king; and the
liſt is entred ſpecially on theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles: <hi>Of the Kingdome of
Chriſt. The Magiſtrate, Juſtification, Baptiſme, the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the
Lord, the incarnation of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>marriage.</hi> Wherein they
went ſo farre by proofe of Scripture that the man, for all his wraſtling to
make good his ground, was, though not fully turn'd, yet bent and weakned ſo
that at the laſt he almoſt granted all. Which yet 'tis thought he did in
hopes to ſave his life. For when they came the ſecond time unto him he 
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:107072:37"/>promiſed, if he might be ſpared, that he would make the
Anabaptiſts growne ſo numerous in <hi>Holland, Brabant, England,
Friezland,</hi> all to be ſtill and ſubmit in all things to the
Magiſtrate. The ſame men then enter diſputation with his fellowes, both
by word and writing, Of <hi>Mortification, Paedobaptiſme, Community</hi> of
goods, and the <hi>kingdome of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <head>CAP. XXVI.</head>
            <argument>
               <p> The Kings diſcourſe with the Biſhop. His and his fellowes
Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>WHen they were brought to Talget, the King being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by the
Biſhop, by what authority he durſt to arrogate ſuch licence on
<hi>his</hi> City and <hi>his</hi> people? Askes him againe, and who gave him
the Rule and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there? when the Biſhop anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that he had it by
conſent of the <pb n="60" facs="tcp:107072:38"/>Colledge and the people: he replyes God
called him thither. Then on the 19 day of <hi>January</hi> they are brought
back to <hi>Munſter</hi> and put in ſeverall priſons. The ſame day
alſo thither came the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and with him the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates</hi>
of the <hi>Archbiſhop of Colen</hi> and <hi>Prince of Cleve.</hi> The two
dayes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing were ſpent in godly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to reclaime them from their
errour, and the king indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed his ſin, and praying, made his
application unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> for Succour. But the other two neither did
acknowledge any fault, and ſtiflly ſtood upon their vindication. Next day
the <hi>King</hi> brought forth upon a ſcaffold is bound unto a ſtake. Two
Executioners are ſtanding by him, and tongs burning hot. At the three firſt
pinches he ſpake not a word: but afterwards continually im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring God for
mercy, when he had beene torne this faſhion for an houre or more, by a
ſword at laſt thruſt through his heart, gave up the Ghoſt. His fellowes
fared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. Being dead, they are all made <pb n="61" facs="tcp:107072:38"/>faſt in
ſeverall Iron cages, and hung upon the higheſt tower of the City. The
<hi>King</hi> indeede betwixt them both, and about the ſtature of a man above
them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:107072:39"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107072:39"/>
            <head>The POSTSCRIPT, <hi>Of the Tumult late at</hi> Abingdon.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>§. 1.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Indifferent Reader.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome yeares are paſt ſince firſt the <hi>ſtory</hi> and
its <hi>preface</hi> gone before were dreſſed and ready in that very garbe
(unto a little trimming) now thou findſt them in, but had never put the foot
(I am perſwaded) over the threſhold of their owne doore, no not ſo much
as to take the ayre with a freind or two, much leſſe to have rambled up and
downe the Country at this rate they do, had not <pb n="64" facs="tcp:107072:40"/>the
<hi>ſad condition</hi> of a froward age, and <hi>ſerious conſcience</hi>
of ſerving ſoules (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps thine owne for one) <hi>to paſſe</hi> by
<hi>freinds deſires,</hi> conſpired in a reſtleſſe importunity to
force them to this poſture. What relliſh the <hi>Eſſay</hi> it ſelfe,
or this <hi>profeſſion</hi> concerning it will find with <hi>perſons
over-byaſſed</hi> by the prejudice of their owne ſpirits; conſequently,
what returne of thankes at the <hi>ſame hands</hi> ſuch a venture will
bring in, needs <hi>no diviner to preſage.</hi> However, on ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall
that the coſts, when well <hi>caſt up,</hi> will not enflame the
<hi>totall</hi> paſt poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of being cleer'd off even to a token,
and ſomething ſpare, by the <hi>meere aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the deſignes
integrity nakedly to promote the publique intereſt</hi> (as is the caſe,
nor quite forſaken of all hopes to ſpeede therein) I hope the ſuppoſed
<hi>inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> will be ſomewhat ballanced, and this <hi>attempt</hi>
of Chriſtian ſervice ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently <hi>abetied.</hi> That we are all apt
to be ſo fond of the <hi>Bird of our owne neaſt</hi> ſo to fancy the
iſſues of our owne minde, as to make our jealouſy burne like frie: at
whatſoever carryeth <hi>but the appearance</hi> of a non-compliance with this
our in dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, is not to be denyed: Oh that <pb n="65" facs="tcp:107072:40"/>it were
bewailed! What other reaſon (to inſtance there) can be aſſigned that
ſuch a <hi>ſignall Monument,</hi> as this Munſter tragedy is, of the
Almighties vengeance <hi>againſt mans turning grace in to
wantonnneſſe,</hi> ſhould be ſo much out of credit with the preſent
ſucceſſours of their faith and practice (at leaſt from whence they are
denominated) that inſtead of being looked upon, and trembled at, and warning
tooke thereby, 'tis cauſe enough, but with <hi>too many of them,</hi> to
enroll him for an <hi>enemy</hi> (in deſpite of the pureſt ayme to <hi>act
the freind</hi> therein) that ſhall perſwade thereto. It is ſomewhat
lighter I confeſſe ſince a chiefe Apoſtle hath beene put to that
Apology, <hi>Am I therefore become your Enemy becauſe I tell you the
truth?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16 (<hi>P.</hi> 2.) A
<hi>[Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of things with us]</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>§. 2.</head>
               <p>But the proofe of this is now no longer <hi>beyond the
ſeas,</hi> having landed on <hi>our Coaſts</hi> ſome yeares agoe, and
taken up its Quarters in <hi>every County</hi> (if not moſt townſhips) of
the Engliſh Nation. Our wonder is the leſſe becauſe (though more is the
pity, and the rather that <pb facs="tcp:107072:41"/>
                  <hi>it</hi> is ſo litle laid to heart)
the <hi>Old knowne enemy</hi> to all concernments of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity having
bankrupt <hi>there</hi> both <hi>caſh</hi> and <hi>credit</hi> is ſhuffling
the cards to play ore his game (once more) <hi>with us,</hi> Their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation
(that it may be would be <hi>game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi>) unto this ſuggeſtion,
<hi>as ſavoring purely of a ſpirit overgrowne with melane choly, that
feares its owne ſhadow,</hi> and <hi>cries out when there is none to hurt
him,</hi> may eaſily raiſe duſt enough (ſutably to his method that
chaſeth darkneſſe for his worke, as being prince thereof) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy a
plot without obſervance by a <hi>purblind eye,</hi> but really hath little
efficacy to put off <hi>men</hi> for <hi>trees</hi> to a <hi>firmer
ſight;</hi> and none at all to <hi>bleſſe him with the happineſſe of
a diſſappointment to his feare that labours under it.</hi> For my owne part
without diſſembling (for now it is no time for ſilence when the very
Ecchoes of ſeditious language makes almoſt every hill and vale to ring
againe) to <hi>me</hi> nere did a cloudy lowring morning ſpeake lowder for
ſome ſtormes a brew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then do the <hi>diſcontents</hi> amongſt us
<hi>avowed and triumphed in,</hi> even to the clowding of the very aire with
the ſmoake thereof, portend ſome fire at bottome <pb n="67" facs="tcp:107072:41"/>(with
the gentleſt gale) ready to enflame. Whoever will be at the coſt but by
looking ore the former ſtory, only to obſerve the <hi>Germane
Monſters</hi> ſhape and compare it with that <hi>Embryon</hi> hatching (you
will ſee anon) but alas too faſt in <hi>England</hi> (the ſonle indeede
of actuall inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is, through mercy, not yet infuſed) I ſhall be
confident of finding him remote enough from rejecting this ſad preſage as
<hi>purely Melancholicall.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>§. 3.</head>
               <p>Let us a while ſay nothing of the Bookes in print,<note place="margin">[Grounded on common diſcourſs, &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> although thoſe ſay enough;
let us meddle not with publique prayings and ſpeakings, which yet ſpeake
plaine to the point in hand: only attend a litle unto what is growing unto
<hi>table talke</hi> common diſcourſe in every mouth almoſt of thoſe
reteining to our male-contented ſpirits: What comes it to? <hi>The Saints
muſt rule.</hi> Tis true in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſenſe, but when or how we will
ſpare to aske it here. It ſeemes tis plaine with them, they do not then as
yet; do not they meane <hi>themſelves alone</hi> can any thinke? Why elſe
one dram or <pb n="68" facs="tcp:107072:42"/>two of charity left for <hi>the people not
their owne,</hi> would bid them ſpare the paines of ſeeking what they have
already. <hi>The ungodly muſt come downe,</hi> we do not doubt it neither, in
the ſenſe of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtill. But who are they, if the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alwaies
muſt be their owne (as to be ſure it ſhall when once they rule the
roaſt) May I ſpeake the feares of others the honeſt <hi>Presbyterian</hi>
and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependant</hi> will be in the number: or, which comes to one the
godly, not of their perſwaſion? Elſe, for the <hi>ranting royall
Enemy</hi> 'tis ſeene by all he is humbled pretty well allready: at leaſt
is not a man of Power now, and therefore not <hi>therein</hi> intended. The
<hi>preſent Powers,</hi> how litle mercy have they at their hands? <hi>Not of
God, injuſt, apoſtaticall, illegall, tyrannicall, perſecuting,</hi> and
enough of this kind toſſ'd like a football up and downe the Country: More,
<hi>Muſt not be payed to, nor prayed for,</hi> and <hi>this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall
too</hi> within our obſervation. And pray why not reſiſted next? Though
one told me (upon an Item given of the Munſter buſineſſe) ſome of
them (the modeſter belike) thought it not <hi>convenient</hi> ſo to do. By
what of mine <pb n="69" facs="tcp:107072:42"/>owne eares, and by what of other honeſt mens
reports, I meet with, beſide their bookes, Reader, I may be well content to
heare thee ſay, as <hi>ſhe</hi> once did in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſſe: <hi>The
halfe is not told me.</hi> And now, can any man that is well in his wits, how
ere the matter may be blanched over to any excuſe, pretence or varniſh
whatſoever, forbeare to ſay, <hi>What meanes this bleating in mine
eares?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>§. 4.</head>
               <p>Whether the <hi>buſineſſe late at A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingdon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[The
Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faireslate at <hi>Abingdon</hi> conſidered]</note> in the County of Berks,
the rumour whereof hath beene upon the wing ere this no doubt unto the utmoſt
limits of Engliſh ground, contributes any farther evidence, and what that is
to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready juſt ſuſpition comes now to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. That the
waies are ſo blocked up from thoſe mens comming at any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of
intelligence in that affaire, whoſe habitations are remote (ſuch to be
ſure as either weare the ſame livery with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or otherwiſe,
whoſe over fond credulity will diſpoſe to any inpreſſion) by a moſt
<hi>lame report</hi> (to ſpeake moſt <hi>ſoftly</hi>) the parties
delinquent thence have <pb n="70" facs="tcp:107072:43"/>thruſt upon the Nation in a
<hi>ſingle ſhee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted pamphlet,</hi> muſt be confeſſed by all whoſe
eyes have <hi>coaſted</hi> on it. And yet I nothing doubt, but that a
perſon of indifferent apprehenſion <hi>(provided all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies his affection be
none other)</hi> upon due peruſall of that <hi>complaining Teſtimony,</hi>
for ſo tis ſtyled, will neede no <hi>Index</hi> for directing him to find
firme bottome that may beare a <hi>ground peece</hi> of ſtate diſturbance
faſtened on it. A peece (with good leave of the Reader, to begin the Account
intended, with firſt caſting up how much that comes to) ſo every way (in
mine opinion) <hi>paſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming,</hi> that its parents, notwithſtanding
naturall fondneſſe, have cauſe enough to <hi>diſinherit</hi> it, yea
never more to <hi>looke upon it as their child.</hi> In earneſt, if one
ſilly ſheet of paper (for tis no more) may po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſibly <hi>breed
bate</hi> twixt <hi>Folly, Falſehood,</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> whoſe
ſhare is greateſt in it; <hi>I</hi> thinke <hi>tis here.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[Which is found fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guilty of]</note> Having once but cleerely
ſhewed how the <hi>Competitours</hi> lay their ſeverall claymes, Ile leave
the controverſy undecided as I find it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:107072:43"/>
               <head>§. 5.</head>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>(1)</hi> [Folly]</note> to create
the expectation of a <hi>dolefull tragedy,</hi> ſay, to hang forth ſome
<hi>Hercules Furens</hi> dyed deepe as ſcarlet from top to toe with the blood
of next &amp; deareſt relations: and then to entertaine the <hi>Longing
ſpectatour</hi> with the cruell murder of <hi>a man of ſtraw,</hi> or to
demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the gaping mortall wounds made on a litle finger by a merciles
pin, drawne from the ſleeve its ſcabbard: I aske, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the merits of
ſuch a cauſe may fairely plead <hi>not guilty of childiſh vanity,</hi> or
juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make complaint it is nicknamed, if any chance to call it
<hi>trifling,</hi> and <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous.</hi> If this be not of kin, yea
coſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>germane to the caſe in hand upon the evidence the <hi>paper
mentioned</hi> it ſelfe gives in, I'le aske no mercy at the hands of <hi>any:
if ſo,</hi> I thinke there is as little neede to feare the cenſure. The
<hi>lintell of the doore</hi> hath written on it, I meane the <hi>Title
Page</hi> cryes out,<note place="margin">[In ſad cryes]</note> of <hi>ſore
calamity</hi> nay <hi>inhumane dealings</hi> of officers and ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers
(repeated pag. 1) that is, a behaviour of them <hi>befitting bruits not
men:</hi> no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <pb n="72" facs="tcp:107072:44"/>then to heare of ſore calamity.
Whoſe pitty <hi>now</hi> would not this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke? Goe on your firſt ſtep
in the <hi>Entry</hi> (the firſt Epiſtle) ſhewes you <hi>contempt,
deſpight, reproach;</hi> yea <hi>ſufferings</hi> and
<hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations,</hi> under which they are. Really if ſo, and undeſerved
too, 'twould make ones heart to ake. At the <hi>other end</hi> (the ſecond
epiſtle) there you may run and read a ſad complaint indeed of
<hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Cruelty,</hi> and <hi>blood of Brethren.</hi> Whoſe
bowels would not yearne to heare the ſtory of one brothers plucking out,
<hi>as it were,</hi> anothers heart, and waſhing his hands in the very blood
thereof? Were this the caſe, no marvell though they call it <hi>a darke and
gloomy day,</hi> as twice they do in the <hi>breath</hi> of the firſt
<hi>roome,</hi> or <hi>page</hi> you come at.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>§. 6.</head>
               <p>But yet alas! when all doth come to all,<note place="margin">[Without all cauſe]</note> what is this ſaddeſt matter, if
we take their owne bare word for all? View well the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> (I
wiſh themſelves would do it) and there you find (upon all their moſt
<hi>unſufferable provocations) One had his hawking bag ſearched and 
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:107072:44"/>tis ſaid writings (happily ſeditious) taken out. Others
even for (no better then calling) they ſay, comparing the Commander and his
party to their very faces unto high way men (for anſwering</hi> but as
Souldiers <hi>to their petulant challenges of them upon their Orders and
Commiſſion) commanded to their chambers, and for their inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies in
that carriage, caned by him. Some at their meeting houſe doore by the</hi>
Guard, <hi>there ſet (of ſouldiers it ſeemes, and with their piſtols
too, and in their hands belike) hindred from going in. And in particular one
living there had a piſtoll preſented (it may bee fixed for they ſay twas
cocked) to his</hi> breaſt (<hi>not</hi> back) <hi>when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing in. At
the laſt and worſt aſſault (when faire meanes could do no good Reader
aſſure thy ſelfe) They tell you one was pulled downe from ſomething
that he ſtood upon. Another to get out of the way ſtumbled over ſtones to
his hurt. A third offered to be rode over, but not come at. A fourth had many
blowes made at him, but was touched by none. A fifth had his hat ſlaſhed
in</hi> three or foure <hi>places, &amp; which is worſt of all, the</hi>
Commander <hi>cut divers.</hi> But who, and what they were: what danger in
their wounds; where they lie <pb n="74" facs="tcp:107072:45"/>under ſurgeon, with ſuch
like <hi>weighty circumſtances;</hi> No, not a word. It was ſuch a fray
that though they write, <hi>ſome had their clothes torne, and ſome were
haled (not dragged upon the ground) about the market place:</hi> yet how many
were ſlaine upon the place, how many mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded, or how many utterly
diſabled we muſt goe ſome where elſe to be informed. This is <hi>their
ſtory,</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der (mine account whereof I truſt upon thy ſtricteſt
ſearch will paſſe for current: moſt ſure I am with <hi>care</hi> and
<hi>conſcience</hi> it hath beene called to the teſt) this is, I ſay
<hi>their ſtory</hi> ſerved in with <hi>ſore calamity,</hi> with
<hi>cruelty</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> as more thou heardeſt but now. VVhich
what it makes on the firſt <hi>Claimers</hi> ſide, Ile leave un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy
ſelfe: but with preſumption that ſome ſilent thoughts at leaſt will
tell thee thy paines &amp; patience have juſt their amends, who gaping
<hi>out of breath,</hi> to ſee the <hi>mighty monſter</hi> (doubtleſſe)
which a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine fallen in travaile would bring forth, at laſt perceive
there comes a <hi>little mouſe.</hi> As for <hi>their parts</hi> when they
complaine of hard meaſure, that their <hi>nakedneſſe</hi> is ſo taken
notice <hi>of,</hi> and withall acquit themſelves of the <hi>imputation</hi>
of <hi>immodeſty</hi> 
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:107072:45"/>ſo too, <hi>themſelves,</hi>
uncover it in publique view, we are content to ſtand obliged for giving
better ſatisfaction to them. Meane while, having <hi>but once</hi> enquired
what elſe ſhould meane this querulous and unreaſonably whining ſpirit,
ſave to <hi>lay low</hi> (with thoſe <hi>tame ſoules</hi> they deale with
<hi>blindfold;</hi> for an <hi>open eye</hi> ſees in it nothing elſe but
<hi>very chaffe</hi>) the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> who give
ſuch hardeſt meaſure: and to <hi>raiſe</hi> their owne, who
<hi>quietly</hi> put it up. and <hi>added,</hi> that if ever thoſe
<hi>worthies, Heb.</hi> 11. (to looke no further) ſuffered <hi>but at,</hi>
and yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained <hi>after ſuch a rate,</hi> Ile never truſt mine eyes
againe. We will hearken unto what comes next.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>§. 7.</head>
               <p>Then whether <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>conſcience</hi> do not
ſuffer ſomewhat more than <hi>meere reſtraint,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>(2)</hi> Falſehood.</note> I meane flat
<hi>baniſhment,</hi> at the hands but of too many <hi>paſſages</hi> in
that <hi>Paper,</hi> could I be heard, I would beſeech themſelves well to
conſider. To take the teſtimonies but of two or three, enough to make a
valid proofe if they ſpeake home to the point in hand, if not, I 
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:107072:46"/>muſt profeſſe they are <hi>Barbarians</hi> unto me,
or <hi>mute as fiſhes.</hi> For inſtance. Firſt where they call it
<hi>now</hi> a day of their <hi>ſore calamity,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[In
notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of their-owne and—]</note> elſewhere amplified
(as tis well knowne) by words of heavieſt weight and ſaddeſt import,
<hi>contempt, reproach, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But is the matter <hi>thus</hi> indeede? Or is it poſſible
<hi>themſelves alone</hi> of all the world ſhould ſee tis ſo? What are
thoſe preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures lying on them that fetch ſuch ſighes and groanes
from their very hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? If we go round the Nation, and aske their
Neighbours in every tything, who can acquaint us with them? May we not, Reader,
muſt we not ſay unto them, as the Apoſtle did to others, <hi>who is he
that will harme you if ye be followers of what is good?</hi> Are not their
<hi>liberties</hi> &amp; their <hi>Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> aſcertained to them by as
good a <hi>title</hi> as any other perſons whatſoever. Yea by as good a
title as unto the <hi>Preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> it ſelfe, I meane the
<hi>Inſtrument.</hi> Who doth not know that <hi>theirs</hi> and <hi>its</hi>
muſt live and dye together, unleſſe <hi>themſelves</hi> lay violent
hands on <hi>either</hi> before the time. <hi>And are they not in
poſſeſſion of them?</hi> Ah worſt ingratitude to the hand of mercy,
that puts <hi>ſweete for bitter,</hi> and <pb n="77" facs="tcp:107072:46"/>
                  <hi>bitter for
ſweete,</hi> that nicknames <hi>light darkneſſe,</hi> and
<hi>darkneſſe light, good evill</hi> and <hi>evill good!</hi> And can a
gracious ſoule forget or ſlight the bitter word againſt that evill frame
of ſpirit?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſay</hi> 5.20.</note> All that is ſaid,
or poſſibly <hi>can be</hi> (whereof I am aware) which whether heavier than
the <hi>duſt of the ballance</hi> is quickly tryed, comes but to this,
<hi>ſome</hi> (very few) <hi>of their freinds are kept in Priſon.</hi> And
muſt <hi>their freinds</hi> (if one ſhould aske them) of all the world
alone be lawleſſe? Is this the liberty contended for (to put that alſo)
that they <hi>ſpeake</hi> what they pleaſe, <hi>do</hi> what they liſt
and no man dare to call them to account? Or if (once more yet)
<hi>Authority</hi> ſhall make ſo bold, and with <hi>their freinds,</hi> for
preſervation of the whole, as to command the paring of a <hi>nayle</hi> or
cutting of a <hi>corne,</hi> is all then gone to wrack immediately? The tender
uſage of that very ſmall and inconſiderable number (if now at all a
number) under reſtraint, is juſt ſo far (their miſcarriages duly
meaſured) from laying ground of halfe <hi>thoſe clamours</hi> gone abroad
about it, that it irreſiſtably obligeth unto gratitude all ingenuous
ſpirits Sympathizing with them. He that heares any thing, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out 
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:107072:47"/>his owne doore,</hi> cannot be ignorant that nothing
leſſe than <hi>flat defiance of Authority with us,</hi> brought them where
they are. A leſſon ſure enough nere taught them by the bleſſed
ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 13-1.</note> whoſe language is
<hi>let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers, becauſe they are the
Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>§. 8.</head>
               <p>Nor doth it ſerve the turne,<note place="margin">[Sions pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly—]</note> only to call it <hi>now</hi> a day of
<hi>their owne calamity,</hi> but <hi>Sion</hi> alſo muſt be intituled to
that complaint: <hi>Sions tribulation;</hi> ſo the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to the
firſt epiſtle hath it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> Sion <hi>only among themſelves?</hi> Let any ſhew
me how that phraſe will faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beare another ſenſe. There is then but
<hi>little Truth</hi> in that I thinke all <hi>other men</hi> will ſay: and
<hi>leſſer love</hi> (me thinkes) I may: but that (alas!) <hi>tis no ſuch
newes to find it ſo with them.</hi> Or if we <hi>ſtraine</hi> their [Sion]
that there may be roome for <hi>other, all Saints elſe,</hi> beſides
themſelves, within theſe Lands to ſhelter under it, tis ſtill as much
an <hi>Alien</hi> unto <hi>Truth</hi> as formerly. <hi>Had indeed the Lord
cauſed the wayes of</hi> Sion <hi>to mourne, <pb n="79" facs="tcp:107072:47"/>becauſe
none came to her Solemne Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies: had the Lord abhorred his</hi>
Sanctuary <hi>that his voyce from thence were no more heard: had the</hi> Lord
<hi>given her walls into the hand of her</hi> Enemy, <hi>that ſhee muſt
hold her</hi> tongue <hi>and not make mention of the name of</hi> Lord. VVere
this, or worſe, <hi>the caſe of the</hi> Sion <hi>here with us:</hi> who of
her <hi>ſons</hi> but his eye muſt needs affect his heart unto a
<hi>dolefull lamentation</hi> for and with her? But, <hi>whilſt our eyes
behold our</hi> teachers, <hi>and ſee the beauty of their feet that bring
glad tydings: whilſt we ſit under our vines and fig-trees none making us
afraid: Whilſt</hi> Kings <hi>are nurſing fathers</hi> to us, <hi>and</hi>
Queenes <hi>our nurſing mothers:</hi> as <hi>here</hi> 'tis thus with Sion
<hi>yet,</hi> and ſomewhat better (adored be that <hi>grace</hi> from whence
tis ſo) it cannot ſinke into our thoughts but as her <hi>heart</hi> is
filled with joy and <hi>mouth</hi> with <hi>laughter</hi> hereupon, ſo her
<hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> will find ſome fitter matter to ſpend themſelves
upon, moſt likely, <hi>that untoward frame of ſpirit that doth not duly
prize and make a juſt improvement of thoſe ſignall mercies injoyed by
her.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:107072:48"/>
               <head>§. 9.</head>
               <p>I ſhall paſſe by their <hi>frontiſpeece</hi>—
implicite accommodation of the 3 <hi>of Malachy and</hi> 15 <hi>verſe</hi>
unto our times: and diſcharge the <hi>ſecond parties claime</hi> upon the
hearing only of <hi>one evidence</hi> more given in,<note place="margin">[The
groſſe untruth in pleading not guilty under ſuch appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
misbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour]</note> in one <hi>halfe line</hi> in their laſt page. And thus
it ſayes, <hi>Little againſt any was ſpoke or done at the
meeting.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But where is now the ſoft and tender Conſcience that will not
beare falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and dareth thus deliberately in the face of heaven
and earth, and by ſo many <hi>hands</hi> (how few ſoever were the
<hi>heads</hi> about compoſing right <hi>hearts</hi> for certaine
<hi>herein</hi> being feweſt of all) to caſt up, <hi>in print,</hi> ſo
vaſt a bill of <hi>venomed provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> into <hi>very ciphers?</hi> All
was but <hi>litle,</hi> ſay they, but what that <hi>litle</hi> was it
ſeemes they have <hi>more wit</hi> (at leaſt) than tell. <hi>A little
truly</hi> of their <hi>little, Reader, thou mayſt expect to heare anon.</hi>
Meane while I would aske <hi>themſelves.</hi> Is this the part of
<hi>faithfull Hiſtorians;</hi> but no more of that: doth it become honeſt
and upright Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Sons of Sion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>[Teſtim:]</hi> pag. 4. l. 31, 32, 33.</note> to pretend an
exact <hi>Relation,</hi> for preventing falſe reports, with 
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:107072:48"/>acouched obligation on mens conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>at leaſt
their brethrens,</hi> to credit none but theirs: and that too in a
buſineſſe of ſuch moment wherein <hi>all Authority</hi> on one hand is
concerned, and ſome private perſons on the other, upon a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der point,
<hi>Reputation of the deareſt kind, conſcience, piety,</hi> (what not?) and
yet to be ſo groſſly partiall to the eye of every Reader, as on their
<hi>owne behalfe</hi> to put downe pence for pounds or better, and on
<hi>Authorities</hi> neither pence nor pounds at all. Whom will not ſuch
proceedings put in mind of the people that made <hi>lies their refuge,</hi> and
<hi>under falſehood hid themſelves?</hi> Believe it 'tis the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
taske after this rate to juſtify the wicked and condemne the righteous,
<hi>with abundant plauſibility,</hi> that may be thought on. Nere did the
womb of Newgate deliver a <hi>viler wretch</hi> than by this method of
procedure might die a <hi>Martyr,</hi> and leave the blackeſt brand of
<hi>Perſecutor</hi> on his moſt <hi>upright judge,</hi> that paſſed the
ſentence on him. Surely the 9th <hi>Commandement</hi> but well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered
and awfully received, would have marred that <hi>claime</hi> that lyes ſo
<hi>fairely</hi> 
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:107072:49"/>now (or <hi>foulely</hi> rather) for
<hi>falſehood</hi> in that paper.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>§. 10.</head>
               <p>We are come at laſt unto the laſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender that is
<hi>Sedition.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>(3)</hi> [Sedition]</note> To
pronounce it as the <hi>Soule</hi> that animates the whole, would both prejudge
the tryall, and looke too like a paſſing ore thoſe bounds then ſet when
firſt the Champions were uſherd in to play the prize. Let the
<hi>Reader</hi> only take that hint and purſue it further at his owne
diſcretion.</p>
               <p>Not to inſiſt upon the plagues they threaten ſuch as
faithfully will ſerve the ſtate.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi>
2.8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Scornes,</hi> and <hi>raylings, ſlanders</hi> and
<hi>black cenſures upon Authority</hi> it ſelfe: if theſe not
<hi>cypherd</hi> but in <hi>words at length,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[In vile
revilings of Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty]</note> not <hi>ſingle</hi> but <hi>in
companies,</hi> not <hi>once</hi> but <hi>often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times</hi> belched out may
<hi>commence Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> that <hi>Paper</hi> ſure enough hath done all
its <hi>exerciſe,</hi> and is as well fitted for the faculty as a
<hi>vagabond for the Stockes.</hi> What think ye where it ſaies the
ſouldiers had—Orders from <hi>their Lord</hi>—in the firſt
leafe: and one whom—<hi>They call</hi>— M. Gen. <hi>Bridges,</hi>
in the laſt? Tuſh this is nothing: <pb n="83" facs="tcp:107072:49"/>take it by <hi>whole
ſale</hi> (for tis not fit to be <hi>retayled) Apoſtates, Perſecutors,
Traytors</hi> (like Judas) and a <hi>Sodomitiſh generation,</hi> and this no
further off than the <hi>two Epiſtles</hi> is the greeting which they give
our Powers.</p>
               <p>He that can find a fitter name than what I give this language,
ſhall quickly have <hi>me</hi> his diſciple; but whoſoever think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
their <hi>dark</hi> profeſſion (at the cloſe of all) againſt an actuall
riſing <hi>then,</hi> both rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon enough for <hi>ſeeking out another
name,</hi> and a ſufficient ſecurity on their parts, for <hi>keeping of the
peace</hi> muſt give me leave to enter my diſſent. Moſt ſure
<hi>I</hi> am, the bleſſed ſaints of God recorded in the holy
<hi>Scriptures</hi> are not the <hi>Patrons</hi> of this ranting talke. No, we
may learne from them <hi>it</hi> hath another father than that Spirit of
holineſſe, meekneſſe and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which lodged in their boſomes. If
this be newes to any Reader, let him remember what their character is: who
<hi>deſpiſe dominions,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 8.2.
<hi>Pet.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>ſpeake evill of dignities,</hi> and <hi>reſiſt the powers;</hi>
whereto the margent will aſſiſt him. Let him withall conſider ſadly
<hi>(oh that themſelves would do it!)</hi> to whom that Prophecy holdeth out
the finger which telleth us. <hi>In the laſt dayes <pb n="84" facs="tcp:107072:50"/>perillous times ſhall come: For men ſhall be lovers of their owne
ſelves— diſobedient to parents—deſpiſers of</hi> others
<hi>that are good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1.2, 3,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Traytors, heady, high-minded:</hi> and which is the
miſery, all this <hi>under a forme of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, but without the
power:</hi> and much more like it.</p>
               <p>Believe it; all the paint and varniſh in the world improved by
the rareſt <hi>Artiſt</hi> for ſetting of ſuch a rate of carriage as
<hi>ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>divine,</hi> will have alike ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe
(with every <hi>wiſe and ſober Chriſtian</hi>) to the greateſt paines
for waſhing white the <hi>Ethiopians</hi> skin, which is proverbially called
<hi>Labour in vaine.</hi> No, No, with ſuch a one, as their <hi>complaining
Teſtimony</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken for a <hi>new Booke of Martyrs:</hi> ſo
neither is he able to ſhift of his ſaddeſt feares, that ſuch a
<hi>ſpirit</hi> as breathes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in will do its beſt to prove himſelfe
<hi>no baſtard</hi> to his <hi>Progenitors beyond the Seas.</hi> Although it
be his earneſt ſuite at the throne of grace, that an Almighty hand may
diſpoſſeſſe it of <hi>its</hi> hold in gracious hearts, and plucking
<hi>them</hi> as brands out of the burning, fruſtrate its <hi>hopes,</hi> and
<hi>his owne feares</hi> together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:107072:50"/>
               <head>§. 11</head>
               <p>By this time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>(2)</hi> [By a juſt
Narrative of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching—]</note> Reader, (ſuppoſing now
thou haſt as litle mind as I my ſelfe to medle in theſe <hi>Rivals</hi>
quarrell) thou art expecting a juſt <hi>compendium</hi> of that Affaire at
<hi>Abingdon.</hi> And I muſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe there is ſo litle pleaſure to
me in the worke, that were I not herein (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a complement) <hi>devoted to
thy ſervice,</hi> a meere review of what is paſt already would bid me
ſuperſede all further information. But, <hi>for thy ſake,</hi> untill
they pleaſe (who wrote upon the place, all paſſages worthy obſervation)
to gratify their Country with ſo ſmall a Curteſy as the making publique
of their <hi>notes,</hi> I will attempt the <hi>puſhing of the pikes</hi> to
let thee ſhare in part of that exact intelligence freely beſtowed on me
(then abſent, as fell out, though <hi>often</hi> there, and <hi>alwaies
living within ſix miles diſtance of the place</hi>) by perſons, and my
honoured freinds, of <hi>Piety and Prudence,</hi> Spectators of the
Buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr Pendarves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[Mr Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darves his
death]</note> late paſtour to the Adverſaries of Infant-Baptiſme in that
<hi>Towne,</hi> having yeelded up the Ghoſt <pb n="86" facs="tcp:107072:51"/>ſome weekes
before at <hi>London,</hi> and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his many <hi>quarrels</hi> here for
everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting <hi>peace</hi> (I am ſo perſwaded from that intimacy ſome
yeares agoe betwixt us) in our fathers kingdome; after ſome hot debates twixt
his ſurviving freinds about his <hi>bodies</hi> reſting place on earth: was
brought at laſt, by water (in a cheſt like thoſe for ſugar, fild up
with ſand, and lodged at a Grocers) there to depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite the <hi>remaines of
death,</hi> where the <hi>ſervice of his life</hi> had beene devoted. This
brought of perſons (of the ſame complexion with him in religious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters)
out of their reſpect unto his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, from <hi>moſt parts</hi> of the
Nation, and ſome the <hi>remoteſt,</hi> a number of both ſexes (both far
and neere) very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
               <p>The <hi>State</hi> tooke <hi>Item</hi> of the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences the
concourſe of ſo great a people (where diſaffection to our preſent peace
apparently predominates) might ſtart at ſuch an opportunity,<note place="margin">(Knowne to the ſtate)</note> and prudently to prevent the
worſt, aſſigne eight troops of horſe under command to <hi>Major
Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Bridges</hi> to take up quarters, at the very <hi>Juncture,</hi> in
<hi>Wallingford:</hi> a <hi>Towne</hi> within the ſame County, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:107072:51"/>the ſame river, ſeven miles below the place
forenamed.</p>
               <p>All things prepared for the funerall,<note place="margin">[And
Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall with—]</note> and the company met on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 30
<hi>of September</hi> —56 (the day unto that worke appointed) the
<hi>Corps,</hi> with meete ſolemnity, in a <hi>new burying place,</hi> before
a <hi>Garden</hi> (for ſuch a one of late hath beene procured at the Townes
Weſt end, and in the Oxeſtreete: whether becauſe they would not have
<hi>communion with us a live or dead,</hi> or for what other reaſon I muſt
be ſilent) is eſpouſed to the grave. <hi>That day,</hi> ſaving what
time attendance on this evening-worke bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed of neceſſity, was ſpent
upon <hi>Religious exerciſes:</hi> ſeverall, as thereunto drawne forth,
taking their turnes in <hi>praying</hi> and in <hi>ſpeaking.</hi> The
<hi>morrow is as yeſtarday with them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>§. 12.</head>
               <p>But tis ſad to heare at <hi>what a rate</hi> they deale with
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies ſtrange and
ſad beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour there at the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> The burden of that whole
demeanor rings only, as a disingaged perſon will be apt to thinke, of blowing
the match that ſhould give fire unto the trayne layd <pb n="88" facs="tcp:107072:52"/>for
enflaming heaven and earth <hi>againſt our peace and powers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There it was ſaid (with gall enough) <hi>The treacherous dealers
have dealt very treacherouſly:</hi> and I thinke none want directions for the
application. <hi>There it was told the Lord that he had made</hi> Him <hi>like
to Cain (who ſlew his brother) a vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond, and one afraid where no feare
is.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to make ſure the dulleſt Schollar might underſtand the
perſon aimed at, <hi>t'was added,</hi> therefore <hi>he ſends after us;
Lord bring him downe, we will not give thee reſt untill thou anſwere
us.</hi> There was the <hi>Man</hi> that had <hi>face enough</hi> to ſay,
<hi>God never proſpered our armies by land nor ſea ſince our rebellion
againſt</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>and turning traytors to his kingdome: and,
to ſee the forehead! this notorious falſehood (without a bluſh) ſpoke
to the face of God himſelfe, with ſolemne notice taken of his hand
appearing in it, and farther hopes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed that he would never make it
better with us for hereafter.</hi> Truly this takes the leſſe upon us unto
admiration, ſince ſure enough, <hi>falſe witneſſe</hi> is an evill
hardly of ſo <hi>deepe a dye</hi> as <hi>blood.</hi> And yet the queſtion
being ſtarted there by one in prayer, <hi>whether Gods people muſt be a 
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:107072:52"/>bloody people</hi> (in an active ſenſe) <hi>was
carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſame in the affirmative, who ſpake it with ſufficient
boldneſſe (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever others ſay unto the contrary)</hi> that <hi>they
muſt be a Bloody People.</hi> To make which paſſage good (tis too too
probable) the requeſt was ſent to heaven by him that beg'd importunately
for a <hi>powring forth the ſpirits of Davids Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers on them, whereby
their hands might be taught to war and fingers to fight, that when they had
done all they might give the glory unto God.</hi> Which that it might not die
as a faint deſire in the very birth <hi>was midwif'd</hi> unto life &amp;
vigour by the greateſt care, as of other hands; ſo of his eſpecially, who
in a large diſcourſe drew forth a <hi>parallell</hi> betwixt <hi>Gods
people's</hi> caſe with us, and <hi>Lots in Sodome,</hi> from <hi>Gen.</hi>
19.15. the text he ſpake 'on. Thence (if the Reader will accept a taſt of
what at large lies by me) <hi>he acquaints the people, that Gods people muſt
not ſtay in the plaine, but up to the mountaines and undertake hard things:
with more unto that purpoſe.</hi> The <hi>doctrine</hi> thus commended was
cleared by removall of objections, as from the <hi>hardneſſe of the
diſpenſation,</hi> the <hi>improbabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of accompliſhing the
deſigne,</hi> a <hi>trade,</hi> a <pb n="90" facs="tcp:107072:53"/>
                  <hi>family,</hi> and
<hi>relations</hi> to be attended, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſoule injoyments</hi> within, <hi>beſides outwards, liberty
of Gods Ordinances,</hi> and ſuch like: which all being put together (it was
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed) ſeeme to ſpeake faire for ſitting ſtill and being
quiet. But a wet finger wipes off all. <hi>For tis returned hereto, amongſt
other things, that tis worſe to ſtay in Babylon,</hi> Lot <hi>had got
nothing by ſaying thus: a fiery diſpenſation tis, up then and be gone
leaſt flames ore take you. The call muſt be obeyed, though as</hi> Abram
<hi>did, you goe you know not whither. Nothing that is deare muſt now be
valued. Expect rubs in the way; arugged diſpenſation tis.</hi> Friends,
Relations, great ones <hi>of the Earth, will</hi> oppoſe, <hi>and</hi>
oppreſſe <hi>you. But the worke is Gods, and</hi> he will proſper it.
<hi>If this will not ſalue the ſoare: then the curſe</hi> on Meroz for
not ſubmitting to the preſent diſpenſation in coming forth to helpe the
Lord againſt the mighty; and menacings of Gods fury breaking out againſt
that man, that out of <hi>Jeare,</hi> or a <hi>ſpirit of indifferency</hi>
declines the worke, is brought in to inforce the Exhortation paſt all
reſiſtance. But for the <hi>diſpenſation</hi> talked of, he that would
know what that may be, is ſoone <pb n="91" facs="tcp:107072:53"/>informed by attending
only unto what that <hi>perſon</hi> ſpake thereof, who told the <hi>Major
Generall</hi> upon his examination: <hi>Though it had beene of the</hi> Lambe
<hi>heretofore, yet now it was to be the</hi> diſpenſation of the Lyon. 
<q>
                     <hi>I had almoſt forgot to give you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his</hi>
Revelation, <hi>who, in the peoples hearing, held the</hi> Almighty <hi>very
hard in prayer on a ſpeciall promiſe, made him before he came thither, to
meete him there with ſpeciall preſence.</hi>
                  </q> 
               </p>
               <p>As for the dealing with the <hi>publique preachers of the
Goſpel</hi> at that meeting (to ſave their longing who perhaps deſire
thereof a litle intimation) let it be knowne in briefe, the
<hi>Courtſhip</hi> there <hi>afforded them without diſtinction, Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, dumb dogs, members of Babylon, Antichriſtian
prieſts, and the ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pit.</hi> Save that
<hi>he</hi> ſeemed a litle modeſter, who was complaining <hi>that the
waters of the Sanctuary did run foule, and ſcarcely one in a hundred of them
is able to give a reaſon of the hope that is in them:</hi> till at the laſt
he fauls ſo foule as to praye, <hi>downe with the Prieſts,</hi> without
mercy unto any one at all among them.</p>
               <p>Reader, me thinks, thou ſhouldeſt excuſe me, if I have no
farther mind to <pb n="92" facs="tcp:107072:54"/>rake in ſuch a kennell, tho it would be
eaſy, <hi>from the hands aforeſaid,</hi> to acquaint thee with much more a
kin to this, about both <hi>praying down, &amp; pulling down the Powers that
impriſon Saints,</hi> about <hi>both flat and frequent calling</hi> (SOME
BODY) <hi>Rebell and Traytor,</hi> about <hi>comparing ſouldiers unto Iriſh
Rebels,</hi> about <hi>tearing fleſh;</hi> and ſuch like diſhes,
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in, as common entertainement, within the compaſſe of that
meeting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>§. 13.</head>
               <p>Tidings hereof was quickly brought (for you muſt know there were
that did <hi>by Order</hi> lye leaguer for exact intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence) unto the
<hi>Major Generall.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[Signified to the M. Generall
who—]</note> Who, whether wiſely to give them <hi>rope,</hi> or in
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of their voluntary ſeparation, or (whereto for certaine
reaſons I rather do encline) upon miſinformation given by a <hi>leading
perſon thereabouts,</hi> forbeares, notwithſtanding this ſo juſt and
full a provocation, the firſt and ſecond dayes of their convention <hi>in
ſo publique manner:</hi> for you muſt know that many of them on
<hi>Saturday</hi> before firſt tooke the Towne.<note place="margin">[Sends a
party that-]</note> On <hi>Thurſday</hi> morning a party of ſome fifty
horſe commanded by a <hi>Lievetenant</hi> 
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:107072:54"/>is diſpatched
with Orders to diſſolve the meeting.</p>
               <p>Upon their entrance the pleaſure of the ſtate was publiſhed
to them, THAT THEY MUST DEPART UNTO THEIR SEVERALL HABITATIONS; thoſe that
are ſtrangers that is; for <hi>Townesmen</hi> they are left unto their
liberty.</p>
               <p>This would not <hi>take</hi> upon them, though backed with
importunities both of perſwaſions and intreaties.</p>
               <p>Some had given out before, that they had put up requeſts to God
they waited for returnes unto, &amp; did not know how long they might be kept
in expectation. But the common anſwer was by flat affronts to the Souldiers
faces. A guard was ſet upon the houſe they met in, that they might not
enter there. The multitude cut ſcores for that, and <hi>hurry to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket
place.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[Under greateſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and bittereſt
provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion]</note> There in the <hi>Cryers Pulpit</hi> they begin to
<hi>pray</hi> and <hi>ſpeake,</hi> or rather <hi>rant and raile</hi> in wild
confuſion. Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Protector;</hi> and the <hi>Souldiers</hi> to
their very teethes. <hi>There one cryes out now</hi> Lord <hi>appeare, now or
never for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding of theſe thine and our Enemies.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, <hi>we
are not for</hi> Cromwels King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <pb n="94" facs="tcp:107072:55"/>
                  <hi>for</hi> Prieſts
<hi>and</hi> Univerſities, <hi>but for the Kingdome of Chriſt.</hi> Whole
arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls more of <hi>Billingſgate flowers,</hi> far fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed indeede, but at
the cheapeſt rate were there put off that might be. The <hi>female ſex</hi>
meane while encouraging the <hi>Tumult-leaders</hi> with their acclamation,
<hi>Hold on ye Sons of Syon.</hi> One paſſage more at leaſt is worth your
noting, I meane that mans <hi>Adventure,</hi> who in the market place calls for
a ſigne from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in hearing of that great aſſembly, though alſo
know 'twas with alike ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to thoſe that <hi>had no voyce, nor any
anſwering, in the</hi> 18 <hi>of Kings the</hi> 18 <hi>and the</hi> 26. O the
amazing patience of him that ſeeth <hi>ſpight and miſchiefe,</hi> which
he can with eaſe requite, and yet forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth!</p>
               <p>When at the laſt their contempt and obſtinacy was growne
inſuperable,<note place="margin">[Diſſolves the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.]</note> either by
requeſt or by commands, the <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> were conſtrained with their
<hi>owne hands</hi> to pull downe the <hi>ſpeakers,</hi> and ſo to make
diviſion of them. But of all the <hi>miſchiefe</hi> done in ſuch a
tumult, at ſuch reſiſtance, by <hi>Canes,</hi> and <hi>Swords</hi> (for
the Guns it ſeemes were ſilent) <hi>whatever it were,</hi> I cannot learne
unto this day, <pb n="95" facs="tcp:107072:55"/>though I live ſo neare, and have often
ſince been upon the queſt among <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> and <hi>others,
there</hi> and <hi>elſe where,</hi> who <hi>hath a wound to ſhew for that
dayes work.</hi> The worſt that ever I met with, and <hi>that was from
themſelves</hi> (for I will not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly conceale a little worth the
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring) was that <hi>ſome body,</hi> who I know not, was ſlightly
ſcratched upon the noſe (as others tells me) by a Souldier in the drawing
forth his ſword: and another <hi>individuum vagum</hi> cut upon the hand.</p>
               <p>This being over, the <hi>Major Generall</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with his
whole <hi>Brigade</hi> of horſe, and having called before
<hi>himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>cheifeſt officers</hi> the principall
ſomenters of that <hi>Seditious Buſineſſe,</hi> aſſayes, not meerly
by <hi>extreame civility,</hi> but <hi>freindly and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
tenderneſſe</hi> to reduce them to ſobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety. But with what
ſucceſſe? None would acknowledge, as to owne, the preſent Government.
Many, <hi>even hoyes,</hi> with heads uncovered would diſpute <hi>it</hi>
with him. And others would <hi>not engage for Peace,</hi> not knowing, as they
ſaid, how ſoone they might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
called out to do the Lords work.</p>
               <p>Upon the iſſue of this whole affayre but <hi>only five</hi> of
all that number (where <pb n="96" facs="tcp:107072:56"/>the common ſignall of a Mutiny
<hi>[they were all one]</hi> was often given out) were committed unto cuſtody
(though ſince,<note place="margin">[The iſſue of all, with]</note> 
                  <hi>I
heare,</hi> releaſed) for further anſwer to their misbehaviour. Yet what
<hi>a ſtirre</hi> is made about it: much rather, at how <hi>cheap a rate</hi>
a tumult of that nature was appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I think is worthy admiration. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;
thou haſt the <hi>ſumme</hi> and <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of what upon this
ſubject came to my hands from perſons, as I told, thee of
<hi>unqueſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable credit:</hi> whereto (without the breach of modeſty, I
nothing doubt) I may and do profeſſe a faithfull adherence on my parte from
firſt to laſt. And if thou wanteſt yet ſome <hi>fuller evidence</hi>
for ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thy Judgment on the iſſue of ſuch ſtrange
behaviour,<note place="margin">[Intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spring and head
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.]</note> I thinke thou wilt not looſe thy labour by conſulting
only GENERATION WORK Part 1. eſpecially pag. 23.24.110. compared with a
<hi>Sermon,</hi> ſometime preached in Abingdon, a ſhort account whereof
thou haſt, in an Appendix to <hi>Church-Rules for Abingdon,</hi> publiſhed
by the <hi>Miniſter</hi> there, who heard it preached without the leaſt
reply thereto unto this day, though long before <hi>his</hi> death, whoſe
buriall did give life unto <hi>The Tumult.</hi> That the <pb n="97" facs="tcp:107072:56"/>
                  <hi>Morall Law,</hi> for inſtance <hi>[thou ſhalt not kill]</hi>
ſhould vayle the bonnet to a <hi>[diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation meerely]</hi> calling
unto <hi>blood!</hi> The Lord awaken ſoules and make them try before they
truſt.</p>
               <p>Preſuming now at laſt, thou art as wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as my ſelfe,
having once, good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but expoſtulated a little with <hi>our
diſcontented Brethren</hi> I'le turne thee looſe,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>§. 14.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sirs,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>Will you vouchſafe to caſt an eye (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different) on a few
lines,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>(P. 3.)</hi> [An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation with our
diſcontented Brethren, about]</note> that do proteſt (as farre as
poſſibly their utmoſt intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with their Maſters mind can reach) have
nothing elſe before them but <hi>your reall ſervice?</hi> An <hi>almes</hi>
(me thinks) <hi>ſo cheape,</hi> you ſhould not grudge (ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you at
the leaſt as have not <hi>ſealed Indentures</hi> unto <hi>ſullen
Paſſion</hi>) an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt beggar, ſuppoſe him <hi>freind,</hi> or
<hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is it then that ayleth you to make this noyſe,<note place="margin">[Their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and]</note> and ſtirre you do?
Why cannot the Nations reſt in peace all long of your diſturbance? Who is
the <hi>Man</hi> that doth, or dares entrench upon your <pb n="98" facs="tcp:107072:57"/>priviledges, but at his perill, and on whom you may be righted, if you
liſt to make complaint? Is not the ſeife ſame <hi>ſcope,</hi> and
<hi>elbow roome</hi> allowed you in all <hi>concernments,</hi> as any the good
people of the Nations whatſoever? Wher's any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lord</hi> and
<hi>Maſter</hi> of your faith, but whom your ſelves ſet up? Are not your
<hi>meetings</hi> for doctrine and for practice left to your owne diſcretion?
Can you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine the <hi>beames of ſupreame Power</hi> light with a fairer
and fuller influence on the <hi>otherwiſe minded,</hi> than thoſe of
<hi>your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion?</hi> Name the capacities for <hi>Honour</hi> or
<hi>Advantage</hi> (or what you pleaſe that is worth the naming) whereto your
<hi>meere Profeſſion</hi> can give a non-ſuite to your claime. Do not all
men ſee <hi>many your freinds</hi> (for we preſume your ſelves do not
think the ſeverall merits of them all can mount ſo high) in <hi>Court,</hi>
and Camp, <hi>in Councill</hi> and in Country, <hi>Stars of the greater
magnitude?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>§. 15.</head>
               <p>The <hi>premiſes</hi> are ſo above board in open view to
all,<note place="margin">[Paſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, compared]</note> that I am
ſo little ſolicitous <hi>about your owne conceſſion</hi> of them, as to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:107072:57"/>be confident <hi>very ſtrangers</hi> in our Iſrael are
apt to think the diſeaſe lyes not in periſhing for <hi>want,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[Paſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, compared]</note> but <hi>taking ſurfet
by exceſſe.</hi> Look back a little; how long is it ſince the world was
made beleive <hi>farre leſſe than this</hi> would have ſerved your turne?
Can your ſelves forget <hi>the time wherein</hi> you bare in hand, might you
<hi>but</hi> at the laſt reach <hi>but</hi> to <hi>liberty in Gods
worſhip,</hi> you ſhould ſit downe as at your journeyes end? This, O
this, the very <hi>darling</hi> of our hearts, and <hi>life</hi> of ſoules
(the ſpeech then went) would <hi>make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends and over meaſure to ſighes
and groanes, to prayers and teares, to coyne and blood adventured for it.</hi>
And now the <hi>treaſure</hi> is landed with Intereſt for its ſtay ſo
long, and both injoyed, not yet to be <hi>conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> nay to cry out
<hi>all's loſt and ſhip wrack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> whom doth not this amaze? who can
unriddle it? Say, yee had ſomething (we know not of) to <hi>ſtop our
mouthes</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, will it ſerve to <hi>ſilence Providence</hi>
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo? What think ye, Sirs, when <hi>Egypt</hi> is left, the
<hi>wilderneſſe</hi> over, the <hi>Sea</hi> paſſed, the
<hi>Egyptians</hi> dead upon the ſhoare, yea the <hi>land of promiſe</hi>
viewed already, and ready to be entred on: if the people now (prompted by an
unhappy faction) will <pb n="100" facs="tcp:107072:58"/>be complaining ſtill, as if they
were at <hi>their brickes and laſh;</hi> if <hi>Moſes</hi> and
<hi>Aaron,</hi> the inſtruments of their deliverance, muſt be <hi>kicked
off with ſcorne</hi> for all their ſervice; if through their ſides by
<hi>mutinous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mures</hi> and <hi>ſeditious practiſes</hi> the face of
heaven be flowen againſt, and the <hi>whole bundle</hi> of deare bought
mercies quite <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravelled to the very end of the bottome:</hi> what think
ye if the <hi>Lord</hi> diſtaſt this courſe, and declare from heaven
againſt the <hi>Abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> of it in a dreadfull poſture? will
<hi>ſuch a doctrine</hi> learne us nothing in the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication?</hi>
Could there be nothing ſaid in their behalfe, <hi>who ſerve Chriſt
Jeſus in his Goſpell publickly,</hi> but that you might adde farther to
your preſent work of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fly whole <hi>quivers of arrowes,</hi> even
bitter words, againſt them, without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, notwithſtanding their
beſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you in the Apoſtles language <hi>where is the
bleſſedneſſe you</hi> (ſometime) <hi>ſpake of? for I beare you
record that, if it had been poſſible, you would have plucked out your eyes
and given them us. Are we therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your Enemies becauſe we tell you
the truth?</hi> I ſay but that you might adde far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (oh moſt ſad!)
endeavours to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the prophecy <hi>John</hi> 16.2. He that kill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth 
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:107072:58"/>you ſhall think he doth God ſervice. Yet, Sirs, to
<hi>raiſe</hi> your ſelves upon the <hi>ruines of your other Brethren</hi>
(for theſe you will not take into the number) or <hi>both</hi> to fall as
footſtooles to a <hi>worſer third,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the riotous waſting
ſuch a ſtock of pretious mercies, and making all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion a
hiſſing and a by-word unto ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, cannot (me thinks) but be of
<hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall conſideration to your owne retired thoughts.</hi> Whether the
face of things now carrying on amongſt you look not this way <hi>too
wiſhly,</hi> who is it almoſt but can reſolve it? oh that your ſelves
would time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly look to it!</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>§. 16.</head>
               <p>For what you talke of (enough at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome truly) <hi>Old
principles are apoſtatized from.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[Conſideration of
their Objections <hi>1</hi> Old prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from,, and—]</note>
If humane frailties in your <hi>ſuppoſed Adverſaries</hi> although our
<hi>Rulers</hi> muſt have (hard meaſure!) no benefit of Clergy at your
hands; if the bleſſing upon <hi>Sem</hi> and <hi>Japhet</hi> when
<hi>Ham</hi> was cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. be not at all regarded; if the
<hi>weapons</hi> of the Ancient Church (preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to by none more then your
ſelves in former daies) <hi>Prayers and Teares</hi> muſt 
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:107072:59"/>be quite <hi>throwne downe,</hi> as never more to be
<hi>taken up:</hi> yet at the leaſt be coole a little, whilſt I aske you,
Will not <hi>all principles</hi> and engagements ſpoken of be eaſily (in
your owne ſenſe) reſolved into this one, PROMOTING SIONS IN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEREST? I am
confident you do admit it. Then further, tell me, Is not <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of
Gods people in their worſhiping of him according to their different
light</hi> (I appeale unto your ſelves, according to what you hither to have
ſpoke and wrote) <hi>moſt eminently the</hi> life and ſoule of SIONS
INTEREST? I take this alſo granted. And I beſeech you now, if taking breath
a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, you put us to the proofe that this <hi>is as the apple of the
eye</hi> unto our preſent Governours, do ye not (bethink your ſelves) make
queſtion <hi>whether fire be hot,</hi> or which comes to one, <hi>doubt of
the Suns being up at noone?</hi> All other <hi>principalls</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to,
from whence you ſay depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is made, when once you make the world
acquainted with them (till when I hope your charity muſt excuſe a
non-attendance on them) if they prove ſuch indeed as can <hi>find their
Regiſter</hi> amongſt the reſt of kin to Sion, I think, a private
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may undertake either to ſhew them <pb n="103" facs="tcp:107072:59"/>ſwallowed
up as rivers in this Sea, or (craving leave) in the ſtates behalfe to
promiſe a ſeaſonable <hi>retrivement</hi> of them. Meane while 'twould
well become us <hi>private perſons</hi> to look to our exemplar, <hi>who made
me Judge?</hi> and move within our proper ſphere, by minding of that worke
<hi>our calling</hi> doth cut out unto us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <head>§. 17.</head>
               <p>And for the <hi>tenour</hi> of all your moanes,<note place="margin">[<hi>2</hi> Chriſts viſible Raigne neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected]</note>
                  <hi>Chriſts raigne is not regarded.</hi> For my part I muſt tell you, it
hath beene of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes refreſhment unto me (the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I confeſſe for
yours and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther angry peoples ſakes) that I ſee juſt cauſe,
even at this day, to pronounce it after David, <hi>The Lord doth reigne let the
earth rejoyce, and the I ſles bee glad thereof.</hi> As for the <hi>viſible
kingdome</hi> whereof you are in travaile in the expectation; at leaſt you
may be told, that <hi>It</hi> is of later date, I meane as to your common
taking notice of it, than thoſe <hi>Engagements</hi> ſpoken of, as revolted
from, and ſo were not <hi>in view</hi> when they were entred. It lies upon
you therefore to acknowledge the dealing is not faire to <hi>raiſe your
level</hi> 
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:107072:60"/>for it on that ground: making complaint of
being falſe (if I miſtake not) to what was ſcarcely thought on, much
leſſe enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to.</p>
               <p>Beſides I hope, your ſelves allow that many <hi>eminent
ſoules in grace,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[Whereof many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doubt,
&amp;—</note> not cleare therein (although not ſimply contradicting it)
are yet as heartily deſirous <hi>as your ſelves</hi> both of their
Maſters exaltation and their owne moſt neare injoyment of him who,
conſequently, did it appeare his mind, could bid as welcome to it (though it
may be to their coſts in ſome reſpects) as others ſeeme to do; and
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not deſerve ſuch weight and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at your hands or
tongues as yet they find. But you may know it hath no litle influence on them
to <hi>ſuſpende</hi> about it, when, beſides what ever may be ſaid as
to the ſeaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>§. 18.</head>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">[Why] <hi>(1)</hi>
                  </note> tis as bright
as day to them, that the deſigne wherewith the Goſpell is filled up to the
very top lookes at a <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> not conſiſting <hi>in meates</hi>
and <hi>drink,</hi> in <hi>worldly power &amp; the like</hi> (ſufficiently
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing doubtleſſe to the fleſhly part) but of <pb n="105" facs="tcp:107072:60"/>another nature, <hi>Righteouſneſſe, and peace, and joy in the
Holy Ghoſt.</hi> To make us <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> not among
men, but <hi>unto God:</hi> triumphers, <hi>through belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,</hi> one
<hi>Hell, and curſe, and ſin,</hi> not by a carnall weapon over all men
elſe, though nere ſo godly, if not complyers with our perſwaſion.</p>
               <p>And then remember,<note place="margin">(2)</note> their
<hi>Lord</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prophecy of him that he ſhould <hi>not cry,
nor lift up, nor cauſe his voyce to be heard in the ſtreet,</hi> as the
mode of earthly Princes is) not only did refuſe to be <hi>made a king</hi> on
earth, but ſeemeth elſewhere to give the reaſon <hi>of it, My kingdome is
not of this world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And</hi> it <hi>doth not yet appeare that ever he changed his
mind.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſide it is no doubt with them but that it was the
<hi>diſciples weakneſſe</hi> (before the powring forth of the ſpirit on
them) which they alſo had received by traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from their Jewiſh fathers
to <hi>expect Meſſiah's reigning in an earthly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(3)</note>
               </p>
               <p>Adde hereto, that the proofe <hi>[of ſuch a kingdome]</hi> is
borrowed onely from <hi>dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker prophecies,</hi> and <hi>obſcurer
paſſages,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(4)</note> in the booke of God, not
written with that <pb n="106" facs="tcp:107072:61"/>
                  <hi>Sun-beame</hi> the <hi>other</hi>
is, wherewith their hearts are taken up. And it is worth your heeding, that as
tis <hi>paſt excuſe</hi> in them, who wretchedly <hi>ſport</hi> the
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures into a <hi>very Allegory,</hi> ſo they muſt <hi>beare their
blame,</hi> who in the prophecies thereof will looke no further than the
<hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſide</hi> of promiſed mercies. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſo
cloathing ſpirituall bleſſings <hi>then</hi> (as likely moſt to take on
children) in the Churches <hi>non-age,</hi> yet <hi>when</hi> ſhe is growne
up in <hi>Goſpell daies</hi> would have her underſtand them in the
ſenſe he meant them. And therefore <hi>more than once</hi> we find ſuch
prophecies of the <hi>old Teſtament</hi> as ſeeme to ſpeake of glory and
advantage to the <hi>outward,</hi> yet in the <hi>New,</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by
<hi>himſelfe,</hi> of thoſe belonging to the <hi>inward man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>laſtly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">(5)</note> their great
experience of ſmall advantage by injoying <hi>ſo</hi> the world at will
unto the ſpirituall part (the reaſon why ſo many good words in the booke
of God we find beſtowed on afflictions) and ſad obſervations of their
unhappy fate (through an apparent hand of God therein) who in an over hot
purſuit of an <hi>earthy kingdome,</hi> quite <hi>loſe</hi> (ſo it falls
out) <hi>the way</hi> onto the <hi>heavenly:</hi> witneſſe the former
ſtory.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:107072:61"/>
               <p>Theſe things caſt up together are thought by ſome to come to
ſomewhat, that may make a <hi>ſober Chriſtian</hi> pauſe upon the
buſineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>§. 19.</head>
               <p>But, put the caſe 'twere paſt all queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that ſuch a
kingdome ſhould ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times be.<note place="margin">[If gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not by Sin to
be promoted, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore—]</note> May we the while do evill that good may
come upon it? Or needeth the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> our lye unto his glory? Or
do ye thinke, (and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to be ſerious in it,) it is his mind we
ſhould pull downe <hi>HIS WRITTEN LAWES IN SCRIPT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE,</hi> to <hi>ſet up
a kingdome ſo darkely written there,</hi> as next to not at all? That nothing
leſſe than this way laies you in the road, you travaile, was ſeene
before, and I therefore hope you neede no <hi>Monitor afreſh.</hi> If <hi>my
words</hi> will not take upon you, at leaſt let the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> have
their errand with you.<note place="margin">[They are Exhorted]</note> 
                  <hi>We
beſeech you BRETHREN ſtudy to be quiet,</hi> doing <hi>your owne
buſineſſe. Beware of ſuffering as evill doers,</hi> or, which is all
one, <hi>as buſy bodies</hi> in other mens affaires, perſwade your
ſelves, 'twere <pb n="108" facs="tcp:107072:62"/>much more happy with us, would we all
make conſcience more to tend the <hi>duties of thoſe Places wherein we
are,</hi> than quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell by our carriage even at Providence <hi>for placing us
unto ſuch duties.</hi> Come, Sirs, lets never pawne the <hi>publique
peace,</hi> the <hi>comfort of our ſoules,</hi> the <hi>credit of our
deareſt Lord,</hi> for ſatisfaction to a <hi>diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented humour;</hi>
which, when it hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured them all, <hi>will ne're be full, whilſt we
have fleſh to feede it.</hi> My heart doth give me, that if many of you did
but ſee unto <hi>the end</hi> that way, you enter now ſo boldly on,
<hi>doth lead,</hi> 'twould make your ſoules ride poſt, with ſwitch and
ſpurre, craving all helpe of heaven and earth, untill you were got out
againe: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, Sirs, it is not uſuall for men <hi>at once</hi> to arrive
at the <hi>very worſt.</hi> No, <hi>our malignant Enemy Satan</hi> leads
<hi>by ſteps:</hi> but when tis downe <hi>a ſteepe</hi> tis hard
reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering; for him eſpecially that <hi>is far gone. One evill ſpirit</hi>
once bad welcome makes roome with eaſe and ſpeede for <hi>ſeven
other</hi> worſer than himſelfe. Who hath not heard that <hi>litle
boyes</hi> creep in at win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes <hi>to open dores for bigger theeves?</hi> Why
do we not lay to heart <hi>how great a <pb n="109" facs="tcp:107072:62"/>matter a litle fire
kindleth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sirs, be intreated <hi>in the bowels of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> to
ſtoop betimes to <hi>Solomons</hi> counſell: <hi>let thine eye looke right
on, and thine eyelids ſtrait before thee, Ponder the path of thy feet and let
thy waies be ſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>§. 20.</head>
               <p>May the Lord ariſe to favour Sion and repaire thoſe
<hi>ſaddeſt gaving breaches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">[The Lord intreated
and]</note> Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and errour with the want of Chriſtian love on every
hand have either <hi>made upon her</hi> or do <hi>keepe open</hi> in her; and
turne unto his people a pure language, that with <hi>one conſent</hi> his
Name be called on amongſt them, and no reſt given him till he make
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the praiſe of all the the earth. And May the <hi>ſame
Lord</hi> in mercy reſcue the <hi>honeſt upright ſoules amongſt
you,</hi> not yet acquainted with the depthes of Satan, from that unhappy
ſnare of being longer made the <hi>ſtaulking horſe</hi> unto the
<hi>Jeſuiticall,</hi> and <hi>Satanicall</hi> deſigne of thoſe, who
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute <hi>Religion, Conſcience,</hi> (what not?) for <hi>homage</hi>
to their accurſed <hi>IDOLS, ADVANTAGE,</hi> and <hi>AMBI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:107072:63"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">[The whole concluded.]</note>This is the
Authors fervent prayer for <hi>Her</hi> and <hi>you:</hi> a freind (how ere you
take him) affectionate unto <hi>Both:</hi> and whoſe ſoule deſireth ever
to be found <hi>in doing nothing againſt the</hi> TRUTH, <hi>but for
it.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Hinton, Berks.</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>December</hi> 26. 1656.</date>
                  </dateline> 
                  <signed>W. Hughes.</signed>
               </closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Miſtakes of the Preſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Epiſt. p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 23 <hi>d. y. ibid. l.</hi> 25.
<hi>r.</hi> no. <hi>Book. p.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>d. ta. p:</hi> 49.
<hi>l. penult. r.</hi> claſhing. <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>to
honeſt ad</hi> people <hi>Poſtſcr. p.</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>marg.
ad</hi> (P. 1. An Apology) <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>Title r.</hi> Abington Tumult
<hi>ibm. l.</hi> 26. <hi>r.</hi> fire. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 12.
<hi>r.</hi> ehuſeth <hi>p.</hi> 68. <hi>l.</hi> 26. <hi>after one ad</hi>
once. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>l. penult. ad</hi> (1. By their owne report)
<hi>p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>in too d. o. p.</hi> 79. <hi>l.</hi> 7.
<hi>d.</hi> the <hi>pag.</hi> 85. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>r.</hi> paſſing
<hi>p.</hi> 95. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>r. title.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
